<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great day, or, A sermon, setting forth the desperate estate and condition of the wicked at the day of iudgement Preached at Saint Andrews in Holborne at London By Nathaniel Grenfield, Master of Artes, and preacher of the Word of God at Whit-field in Oxfordshire.</title>
            <author>Grenfield, Nathaniel, b. 1588 or 9.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02223</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12358</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118555</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853762</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853762</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19157</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02223)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19157)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1205:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great day, or, A sermon, setting forth the desperate estate and condition of the wicked at the day of iudgement Preached at Saint Andrews in Holborne at London By Nathaniel Grenfield, Master of Artes, and preacher of the Word of God at Whit-field in Oxfordshire.</title>
                  <author>Grenfield, Nathaniel, b. 1588 or 9.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 136 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby for Josias Harrison, and are to be sold at the Golden Anchor in Pater noster row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19157:72"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19157:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GREAT DAY, OR, A SERMON, SETTING forth the deſperate eſtate and condition of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Preached at Saint Andrews in Holborne at London.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nathaniel Grenfeild,</hi> Maſter of Artes, and Preacher of the Word of God at Whit-feild in Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. Stansby</hi> for <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias Harriſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Golden Anchor in Pater<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noſter row. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19157:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR GEORGE SPEAKE, Knight, <hi>N. G. wiſheth heartily all</hi> happineſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Wiſe mans cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure concerning the many Booke-makers of his time,<note place="margin">Morbus inſanabilie ſcribendi cacoë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, Iuuenal. Quod de ſcriptis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſpiritu ſanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dici non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de illis, quae vanitas humana exculpit quotidie, <hi>Fayius.</hi> Traditiones, decreta Pontificum, Canones generalium conſiliorum, quoad obſequij &amp; fidei neceſſitatem praeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim refelluntur.</note> mee thinks, as much tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this Writing world of ours, wherein men are almoſt no men, vnleſſe they be men in print; all is but a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentarie vpon the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
<pb facs="tcp:19157:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
words; <hi>Of making many bookes there is no end, Eccl. 12.12.</hi> I wiſh to God that there were once an end (which I feare me, will not bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the world ends) of making ſuch books, as ſerue to no end, but to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting of maners, infecting the hart, weakening zeale; and that ſome good <hi>Auguſtus</hi> would baniſh them, (as hee did <hi>fleſhly</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Amato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae Nafo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus non eſt tutum rudem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erceri, <hi>Eraſmus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ouid)</hi> out of our Bethel, Chriſtian England, into ſome <hi>Betha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> into ſome Idolatrous, Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Heatheniſh Nation, that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Sunne and the Moone, <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> Rats and Mice, in ſtead of the true God of Heauen; or ſent backe for Vagrants into <hi>Italy,</hi> or the Stewes of Rome, where, like an adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous broode, they were firſt borne and bred; or that they were all ſerued with the ſame ſauce,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stapleton.</hi> Praefat. Moral.</note> as (by <hi>Stapletons</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port) Saint <hi>Ephraim</hi> wittily vſed two
<pb facs="tcp:19157:2"/>
bookes of <hi>Apollinaris,</hi> who finding them in a womans keeping, borrowed them of her, and glued the leaues ſo hard together, as the booke could neuer after be opened. For (as one ſaith well) ten Sermons at Pauls Croſſe doe not ſo much good for moouing men to true doctrine, as one of theſe bookes doe harme, with entiſing men to ill liuing; and that more Papiſts are made by the merry bookes of Italy, then by the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt bookes of <hi>Louaine;</hi> ſo that they doe not only win the wils of the weake vnto wantonneſſe, but tend ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the corrupting of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Saint <hi>Iames</hi> reprooues very ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe, that with the ſame tongue bleſſe God, &amp; curſe man, <hi>Iam. 3.9.</hi> why then ſhould the ſame Caracters ſet foorth <hi>Machiauels</hi> workes and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> writings, Chriſt and Belial, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt loue of wanton Heathens, and the
<pb facs="tcp:19157:3"/>
chaſt and reciprocall loue of Chriſt and his Church? But as for ſuch bookes as haue our <hi>Sauiour</hi> for their ſubiect, the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> for their Author, Gods glory for their end; that are like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Cannons planted againſt the Gates of hel, that tend wholly to the demoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Satans Kingdome, vndermining the Bulwarks of Babylon, but building vp the Walles of Ieruſalem, why ſhould not the ſound of ſuch goe foorth into the ends of the world? and when they ſound foorth, the end of the world? To which end, I haue preacht pend, and through the importunitie of others, contrarie to mine owne minde and meaning when I preached, now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed this little Tract and Treatiſe; how free I am from <hi>Salomons</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſuch as print themſelues, let him that is wiſer then Salomon bee a witneſſe: I am bold to fly vnto your
<pb facs="tcp:19157:3"/>
Worſhip, and to entreate you, that you would vouchſafe to bee cald a Patron vnto it, as you are to learning, though farre (I muſt confeſſe) below your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe: The many teſtimonies of your loue from time to time toward my eldeſt Brother and my ſelfe, doe challenge more at our hands, then my penne can expreſſe, or the weakeneſſe of our vtmoſt power make the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall. A handfull of water was fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be powred into a Beggars diſh, then to be preſented vnto a King: yet a King accepted of it, though a beggar gaue it, becauſe he gaue what he had, and had no better to giue: nay, it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God (if we haue no greater gift to offer) to caſt a mite into the Lords Treaſurie: whereby I am indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to conceiue, that you will no leſſe willingly accept of this Paper gift of mine, a Schollars Mite, the trueſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall
<pb facs="tcp:19157:4"/>
of mine intimate affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and manifeſtation of my duty: what is wanting, ſhall bee ſupplied in praying for you vnto God, for your preſeruation, and for an encreaſe in all ſpirituall graces, namely, of faith, which may keepe you from trembling at the day of your death, and in the day of Iudgement. From <hi>Whitfield, Iuly</hi> the <hi>10.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Lord, <hi>NATH. GRENFEILD.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19157:4"/>
            <head>THE GREAT DAY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>REVEL. 6.15.16.17.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>15</label> And the Kings of the earth, and the great men, and the chiefe Captains, and the mighty men, and euery bondman, and euery free man, hid themſelues in the dennes, and in the rockes of moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>16</label> And ſaid to the mountaines, and rocks, Fall on vs, and hide vs from the preſence of him that fitteth vpon the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lambe:</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>17</label>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19157:5"/>For the great day of his wrath is come, and who can ſtand?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Chapter contains in it ſixe parts, and euery part the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a <hi>Seale</hi> by the <hi>Lambe,</hi> and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>ſeale</hi> a diſtinct myſtery: the foure firſt <hi>Seales</hi> being opened, mention is made of foure <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> riding vpon foure <hi>horſes,</hi> of foure different colours, a <hi>white,</hi> verſ. 2. a <hi>red,</hi> verſ. 4. a <hi>blacke,</hi> verſ. 5. a <hi>pale,</hi> verſe 8. vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the beholding whereof, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> was inuited.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Rider</hi> is deſcribed by two adiuncts,<note place="margin">Adiunctis. Arcu. Corona. Effectu. Fine.</note> 
               <hi>a Bow and a Crowne was giuen vnto him,</hi> verſ. 2. Secondly, <hi>by the effect, conquering.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>by the end, to conquer,</hi> verſ. 2.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Seale being opened, the ſecond Rider, which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> was willed for to come and ſee, is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed:<note place="margin">Poteſtate. Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> firſt, by his power, <hi>power was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto him, &amp;c.</hi> verſ. 4. Secondly, by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19157:5"/>
an inſtrument; <hi>there was giuen vnto him a great ſword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Rider is deſcribed by a paire of Ballances, <hi>he that ſate</hi> on this horſe, <hi>had a paire of Ballances in his hand, verſ.</hi> 5. the myſtery whereof is vnfolded by a ſounding <hi>voice,</hi> verſ. 6.</p>
            <p>The fourth <hi>Seale</hi> being opened, there came foorth a <hi>Rider</hi> vpon a <hi>pale horſe,</hi> and the <hi>Rider</hi> is deſcribed, firſt, <hi>by his name, death.</hi> Secondly, by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, <hi>hell followed with him</hi>: and both are deſcribed by their <hi>power; power was giuen vnto them, &amp;c.</hi> verſ. 8. The inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of theſe foure <hi>horſes,</hi> is as my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall as <hi>Nebuchadnezzars dreame,</hi> and may very well beare the ſelfe ſame interpretation, which <hi>Daniel</hi> gaue of that great Image, <hi>whoſe head was of gold, breſt and armes of ſiluer, belly and thighes of braſſe, legges of iron, Dan.</hi> 2.32.33. This Image was an Emblem, or repreſentation of the foure Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies of the World; the <hi>Monarchie</hi> of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> or <hi>Caldeans</hi>; the <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie</hi> of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi>; the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19157:6"/>
               <hi>Monarchie</hi> of the <hi>Grecians</hi>; the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie</hi> of the <hi>Romans</hi>: and as Gold, of all other mettals is the beſt, and pureſt; and therefore it is ſaid, that <hi>Heauenly Ieruſalem is a Citie of pure Gold, Apoc.</hi> 21.18. So White is the beſt, and chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of all colours; and therefore it is ſaid, that the Saints were clothed with white Robes, verſ. 11. Which colour is conſecrated to innocency, puritie, victorie and felicitie; and therefore it is ſaid, that the head of the Image <hi>was of fine Gold, Dan.</hi> 2.32. And that the firſt horſe was <hi>white, verſ.</hi> 2. ſo the firſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, <hi>viz.</hi> of the Caldeans (though full of crueltie) was the beſt, and a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Age, comparatiuely in reſpect of the reſt: but the laſt of all was the worſt of all: the Romane Emperours outſtripped all the reſt, in their bloudy proiects, and vnſpeakable cruelties; for who can reckon vp all their expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of warre, ſo many funerals of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, maſſacring of ſo many millions of men, depopulations and diſpeopling of ſo many Countries, burnings of ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19157:6"/>
many Cities, ſuch a prodigall profuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of blood when this <hi>Roman horſe</hi> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed forth? in ſo much, that the fourth part of the Earth was ſlaine with the <hi>ſword of this fierce Beaſt,</hi> as it is, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. The crueltie of all preceding <hi>Emperors</hi> was clemencie, being compared with theſe <hi>Romans,</hi> whoſe Drummes ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nothing elſe but blood and death, and their little finger was bigger, then the loines of all their predeceſſours.</p>
            <p>The fifth Seale being opened, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw the Soules of bleſſed Martyrs lying vnder the Altar, and crying for reuenge; where firſt hee ſhewes the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of true Martyrs: they <hi>were killed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſeudo-martyrs.</note> (ſo may falſe Martyrs) 'tis a good cauſe that makes a Martyr, and therefore it is ſaid, that they <hi>were killed for the word of God, and for the teſtimonie of the truth, verſe</hi> 9. The words may haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference either vnto the Church Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, who may bee termed Martyrs, though they bee neuer killed, and though they neuer ſtriue to bloud, <hi>viz.</hi> when Chriſtians are rayled at, reuiled,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19157:7"/>
ſcorned, diſgraced, abuſed, falſe witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſuborned, either to empaire the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of their perſon, or empeach the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie of their profeſſion: for the Deuil firſt letteth looſe the tongues of the wicked to ſpeake ill, before he letteth looſe their hands to doe ill. Thus that Protomartyr <hi>Steuen</hi> was gnaſhed <hi>at with the teeth of the wicked, Actes</hi> 7.54. before he was ſtoned; and they ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, which ſaid, Wee haue heard him ſpeake <hi>blaſphemous words, &amp;c. Actes</hi> 6.11. Thus our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> before he ſuffered, endured ſuch contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſinners, accounted ſometimes for a <hi>ſeditious perſon,</hi> a <hi>wine-bibber,</hi> a <hi>friend to Publicans and ſinners, one that had a Deuill,</hi> one that preached falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, &amp;c. And thus <hi>Paul,</hi> before hee ſealed <hi>Peters</hi> confeſſion with his bloud, he was accounted for a <hi>mad man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. l. <hi>10</hi> confeſſ.</note> a <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer of the people,</hi> and for <hi>one not worthy to liue: Lingua impiorum eſt quotidiana fornax,</hi> The tongue of the wicked is a fornace, wherein Gods children are tryed; and there is not a man or mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19157:7"/>
of this little poore deſpiſed <hi>Church,</hi> whether zealous Preacher, or ſincere Profeſſor, but muſt be tryed in this O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of euill ſpeaking: for as long as you are in the world, and are not of the world, <hi>the world will hate you, and ſpeake euill of you, Ioh.</hi> 15.19. Or the words, as it ſhould ſeeme, may in a better ſenſe onely bee referred vnto that heauenly troope of bleſſed Souldiers diſcharged the field, with the <hi>loſſe of life,</hi> and for a reward of this their perſeuerance, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto bloud, are clothed with white Robes; which crie for reuenge, either in reſpect of vs which doe ſuffer (for the Saints in Heauen doe pray for vs in generall, howſoeuer they know not our wants in particular) or in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of themſelues which haue ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, they cry for reuenge (for it is Gods peculiar) either in this life by his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall plagues or puniſhments, or by haſtening his comming vnto Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when they ſhall eternally be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded in that euerlaſtingly burning <hi>Tophet,</hi> prepared for all perſecuting
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19157:8"/>
               <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> who haue made ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocke of the <hi>Saints.</hi> Now the time when this was, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> makes it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that it was after the opening of of the fourth <hi>Seale,</hi> and after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth of the fourth Horſe: for the fierceneſſe and furious rage of this Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Beaſt was not vtterly abated, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there was ſcarce matter left for malice to worke vpon: but no ſooner was <hi>Chriſt</hi> borne, which was when <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Octauius</hi> was <hi>Emperour,</hi> in the two and fortieth yeere of his raigne; and alſo put to death againe, which was when <hi>Tyberius</hi> was <hi>Emperour,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Church</hi> had recouered any ſtrength or growth, but Tyranny wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on her, to deuoure her children as ſoone as they were borne. There are two diſtinct times, in which the <hi>Church</hi> of God ſuffered moſt grieuous perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions; the firſt was in her Primitiue eſtate, when by the preaching of the Apoſtles, the number of beleeuers were multiplied exceedingly; then did the foes encreaſe, that troubled her
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19157:8"/>
peace and proſperity, bearing euill will to Sion, inueigled by that helliſh Dragon, that was ſet at liberty, ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and banding all their forces and furies, proſecuting her with all might and malice, did ſet her againe a bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when ſhee was yet but a budding. Her moſt bloudy perſecutours were theſe Romane bloud-thirſty <hi>Emperors, Domician, Traian, Nero, Doecius, Diocleſian, Antoninus, Maxentius, Lycinius,</hi> and other cruel Tyrants, euen vntil the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great; by whom the <hi>Saints were killed all the day long, and were accounted as ſheepe to be ſlaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond time was in theſe laſt times, vnder Antichriſt, when the whole number of Martyrs ſhall bee compleatly finiſhed, as it is <hi>v.</hi> 11. which may alſo bee diuided into tenne perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, if wee reckon vp all thoſe ſlaughters of bleſſed Martyrs, which haue beene from the time of <hi>Iohn VVickleeue</hi> within theſe 138. yeers,<note place="margin">The firſt perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this time throughout all the coaſts of Europe. As firſt vnder <hi>King Henry</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19157:9"/>
the fourth and fift, here in <hi>England</hi>; the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſecond vnder that generall Councell held in <hi>Conſtantia,</hi> and <hi>Bohemia</hi>; the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> third vnder the <hi>Biſhoppes</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the neereſt Prouinces thereof; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the fourth vnder <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <hi>Emperour</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi>; the fift vnder <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth in <hi>England</hi>; the ſixt vnder <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond in <hi>France</hi>; the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> ſeuenth vnder <hi>Iames</hi> the ſecond, in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
               <hi>Scotland</hi>: the eight vnder <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth in <hi>France</hi>; vnder whoſe raigne there were within the ſpace of one moneth put to death, aboue twenty <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> thouſand of Martyrs; the ninth was vnder Queene <hi>Mary</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> ſhe that was a ſecond <hi>Nero,</hi> for her cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, but yet for the Churches comfort, ſhe was but <hi>Nubecula citò tranſitura</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> A ſhort tempeſt:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</note> for had ſhe liued, then had the Churches chiefeſt nurſing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beene bereaued of her life, and we her children ſhould neuer haue inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe <hi>Halcyonian</hi> dayes wherein the Goſpel flouriſheth in deſpite eyther of <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Turke.</hi> During the time of whoſe raigne, which was but for the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19157:9"/>
ſpace of fiue yeeres, there were aboue forty thouſand liuing bodies of the moſt choiſeſt <hi>Martyrs</hi> moſt cruelly burnt, I ſay, the liuing bodies, to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate the depth of their inraged enuy; for they would not ſuffer the bones of the dead to reſt in their graues, but they muſt be burnt to aſhes, when they were almoſt rotten to the duſt. The <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> tenth was vnder <hi>Philip</hi> in <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Flaunders,</hi> as in the Spaniſh Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we may read more at large; nay, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt what part of the earth hath not that drunken <hi>VVhore</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> moyſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the bloud of Saints? And yet heere is not an end, but ſtill ſhee is plodding and plotting ſome ſecret miſchiefe vpon the bed of her fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and hatching ſtill a malicious brood of Serpents and Cockatrices, Men and Deuils, helliſh conſpiratours, ſtill machinating the workes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, their fellow-helper being the Deuill, which is the Prince of darknes: and therefore no maruell though the Church triumphant in heauen, and the Church militant vpon earth, doe daily
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19157:10"/>
cry for reuenge vpon that <hi>VVhere of Babylon</hi>; and the Lord hearing the lowd cry of the Saints, whoſe bloud cryes as lowd as euer <hi>Abels</hi> did againſt his brother <hi>Cain,</hi> at the length <hi>awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth as one out of ſleepe,</hi> commeth forth as a <hi>Giant refreſhed with wine, ſtrikes their enemies vpon the thigh,</hi> and puts them vnto a perpetuall ſhame; as you may ſee at the opening of the ſixt ſeale, when God, in the ſeuerity of his wrath, ſummons all Kings and Princes of the earth, which haue been bloudy agents in maſſacring of Saints, vnto the trembling Tribunal of his generall Iudgement; where the firſt thing that we may take notice of, is the fearefull alteration of naturall things both in heauen and earth <hi>ver.</hi> 12.13.14. <hi>In the Sunne blackneſſe, the Moone became as bloud, and the Starres fell from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, heauen departed as a ſcrowle, the earth ſhooke, mountaines, and Ilands were moued out of their place</hi>; All which are euident demonſtrations of that great and fearefull Day; <hi>Mark.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 24.25. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. <hi>v.</hi> 29. <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.25.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19157:10"/>
The ſecond is the feare and amazed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of men: <hi>Kings, great men, rich men, chiefe Captaines, bond and free, their hearts did faile them for feare, Luk.</hi> 21.26. deſiring rather that the earth would ſwallow them vp aliue, as it did <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> then to behold the countenance of ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry a Iudge, and breathing forth ſuch bootleſſe exclamations vnto the ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Rocks and helpleſſe Mountaines, <hi>Fall vpon vs, couer vs from the wrath of the Lambe, v.</hi> 15.16. All which doe immediately goe before the day of Iudgement, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17.11. I had rather wade with the Lambe in the ſhallow, leſt with the <hi>Elephant</hi> plunging my ſelfe into the depth, I ſhould be drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the depth; which is a iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God vpon all raſh enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſpirits, and curious inquiſitors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vnſearchable ſecrets and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries paſt finding out of almighty God, to be giuen ouer vnto their owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate ſpirits, and to loſe themſelues in the Labyrinth of their owne ſelfe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and all becauſe they will not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19157:11"/>
confeſſe their ignorance, and content themſelues with a <hi>ſober knowledge, Rom.</hi> 12.3. but wil be wiſe aboue what is written. Once, ſure I am of this, that the Scriptures doe containe in them all things neceſſary to ſaluation, and that they are riddles, and myſteries, darke, and obſcure vnto none, but vnto thoſe that periſh.</p>
            <p>Amidſt variety of Interpretors, ſome inclining vnto a Litterall, ſome vnto an Allegorical, ſome vnto a Tropolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical ſenſe, I doubt not but that I may ſafely lay downe this plaine and litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall expoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> That this Text ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth forth the deſperate eſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the wicked, at the dreadfull day of Iudgement: wherein I obſerue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> theſe parts. Firſt, an enumeration of particulars, concluding an vniuerſall. <hi>Kings, great men, rich men, chiefe Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, mighty men, bond men, free men,</hi> that is, ſome of all ſorts and ſexes; all <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the wicked: Secondly, their ſtraight &amp; deſperate eſtate; in ſeeking ſuch boot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe refuges, <hi>They hid themſelues in dens and in the rockes of Mountaines, v.</hi> 15.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19157:11"/>
Thirdly, their lamentable, yet fruitleſſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> exclamations: <hi>They ſaid vnto the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and Rockes, Fal vpon vs, &amp; hide vs from the preſence of him, &amp;c. v.</hi> 16. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the reaſon of all; <hi>For the Great day of his wrath is come, and who can ſtand</hi>?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Kings of the earth</hi>] not <hi>Romani Principes,</hi> the Princes of <hi>Rome</hi>; that had bin too plaine, and it had bin a meanes to haue exaſperated the malice of thoſe bloudy Emperours more cruelly to imbrue their hands in the bloud of Saints: for Kings that are Tyrants, and rich men that are wedded to the world, can hardly indure to heare of their downefall and deſtruction, but they will rage more furiouſly, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double their cruelty; ſo <hi>Herod</hi> ſlew all the children that were in <hi>Bethlem</hi> and in all the coaſts therof from two yeeres old and vnder, when the Wiſe-men told him that Ieſus was borne, and that <hi>He ſhould be the King of the Iewes, Matth.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 2.16. Therefore Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> noting their power and malice, being that they are <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>rich men,</hi> doth for the Churches ſafety, of ſet pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19157:12"/>
conceale their names: ſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſecond to the <hi>Theſſalonians, c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 3.4. deſcribing the downefall of the <hi>Pope of Rome,</hi> hee calls him not in plaine and direct tearmes, Antichriſt, or the Pope, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>That man of ſin, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, That ſonne of perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which exalteth himſelfe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Aboue all that is called God,</hi> deſcribing the nature of him ſo, that it can be competent vnto none, but vnto the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Vegetius l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> dere mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari.</note>
               <hi>Tribuni, the chiefe Captaines</hi>] ſuch as were ſet ouer a thouſand ſouldiers, ſuch amongſt the Romans were called Tribunes: and a Romane Legion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of ſix thouſand ſouldiers: by which finite agnomination the Deuils ſhewed, that the number of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall Kingdome was infinite, <hi>My name is Legion: for we are many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euery bond and euery free-man</hi>] that is, all the wicked: but eſpecially thoſe that haue beene actors of the Kings decrees, and executioners of new deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed tortures, in the perſecution of the Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:19157:12"/>
               <hi>Hid themſelues in dennes</hi>] Some there are (and that not a few) that would haue this to bee vnderſtood fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiuely of the corrupt eſtate of the Church, and of the laſt perſecution of Antichriſt, when the Popiſh Prelacy had gotten the ſupremacy. The <hi>Sunne,</hi> ſay they, is <hi>Chriſt, blacke</hi> and obſcured, not in himſelfe; but in the hearts of men. The Moone is the Church, which reſembles the Moone waxing and waning; and ſhee borrowes her light from Chriſt. The <hi>Starres</hi> are the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church, Teachers and Preachers of the Word; <hi>Falling to the earth</hi>]. <hi>i.</hi> ſlaine by the wicked, which ſeeme to men to fall to the earth; when as indeede, if faithfull in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours to worke a ſinners conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they ſhine like ſtarres for euer and euer, <hi>Dan.</hi> 1 2. <hi>v.</hi> 3. The Heauen, ſay they, is the ſacred Bible and Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Scripture; containing in it the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed will of the King of Heauen, by meanes whereof we are led vnto Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as the Wiſe-men were to Chriſt by the conduct of a Star,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.39.</note> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 9.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19157:13"/>
Within the Pages of this holy Writ, Chriſt, the Church, the Miniſters, are placed like the Sunne, Moone, and Starres in the Firmament of Heauen; This Heauen <hi>departed</hi> in the raigne of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and became as a claſped Booke in reſpect of the vſe of it, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as good as if it had not beene at all, then the people neuer a iot the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by it, when the Laiety might not read it; but through the Prieſts ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: when Images were Lay-mens Bookes, and ſacred Scripture departed like a ſcrole, that is, lockt vp in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne tongue. <hi>Earthquakes</hi> doe ſignifie ſeditions, alterations, mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> and <hi>Empires</hi>; ſuch as began in the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and doe not end as yet; but ſtill doth that <hi>exceeding dreadfull beaſt, Daniel</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 19. ſtirre vp ſeditions, diſturbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon peace, ſhake Kingdomes, blowe vp Parliaments, cut off and anathemize Kings, by the thunder-bolt of excommunication, yea and afterwards Canonize Deuils for Saints; if they would aduenture to kill Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19157:13"/>The <hi>Mountaynes</hi> are, ſay they, the <hi>Prophets</hi> whom the breath of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt doth ouer-turne, and by the ſame breath of that not erring <hi>Man of ſinne,</hi> doe the Schole-Doctors by their falſe gloſſes and peruerſe interpretations, corrupt, depraue, and ouer-throw the ſenſe of the Prophets.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Ilands,</hi> ſay they, are the workes and writings of Philoſophers, which the ſame Doctors doe peruert ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, beyond the minde and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Philoſophers, ſo that there is nothing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon with the Prophets, nor with true Philoſophie. <hi>Kings and rich men, &amp;c.</hi> are the Monarchs of the world, and other priuate men made ſubiect to the <hi>Popes Catholicall</hi> and <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall Supremacy,</hi> when Kings muſt hold the ſtirrup, and kiſſe the greaſy feet of that triple-crownd Monſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hid themſelues in dennes</hi>] that is (ſay they) the Cels, Cloyſters, Solitary pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Neſts of Nunnes, and vnſociable Monkes. I will not diſallow of this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorizing interpretation, for it may very well ſtand for current: but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19157:14"/>
to the ſimple ſenſe and meaning of the words, as they lye nakedly to be conſidered, and if Scripture may inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret Scripture, the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them playne; expounding this place in the ſelfe ſame termes, or this place expounding that, both ſetting forth the narrow ſtrait, and deſperate perplexity, which the wicked are brought vnto; <hi>They ſhall goe into the holes of the Rocks, and into the Caues of the earth, for feare of the Lord, and for the glory of his Maieſty, when he ariſeth to ſhake terribly the earth,</hi> Iſaiah 2.19. yea, and to ſtrike a deeper dread and horror into the hearts of the wicked, he doth ingeminate it, like that triple <hi>woe</hi> in the eight of the Reuelation, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſaid to the Mountaynes &amp; Rocks, Fall on vs, &amp;c.</hi>] Here the holy Ghoſt doth allude vnto two places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the firſt is the tenth of <hi>Hoſea v.</hi> 8. the ſecond, is the 23. of <hi>Luke verſ.</hi> 30. both deſcribing the deſperate eſtate of the wicked; where our Sauiour ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of a certayne time, when theſe things ſhould be, after hee had ſpoken
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19157:14"/>
of the deſtruction of Ieruſalem, which was a type of the conſummation of the world, and diſſolution of al things; but in <hi>Hoſea,</hi> the Prophet ſpeaketh of the captiuity of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which was a figure of <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> vtter diuaſtation, and the worlds finall deſtruction, as <hi>Hierome</hi> obſerueth vpon that place: It was an old dotage of <hi>Aquinas</hi> vpon this place, who, as his cuſtome is, to turne all things into <hi>Allegories,</hi> doth wreſt this place of <hi>Kings and chiefe Captaines,</hi> and would haue it to be vnderſtood of the Romiſh Clergy, the Biſhops, the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, and the reſt of that rabble, cloiſtred Monks, and Maſſe-muttering Prieſts, <hi>crying vnto the Mountaines,</hi> that is, inuocating the Saints, imploring their patrocinie and their ſafeguarding protection, from the wrath that is to come. But theſe curſed Crue, that rob Chriſt of his honor, who is that <hi>one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mediator,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. <hi>pro quo nullus interpellat, ſed ipſe per omnibus,</hi> as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> defines a <hi>Mediator</hi>; by making as many Mediators as there are Saints departed, ſhal at that day find the Saints
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19157:15"/>
no better then <hi>Iobs</hi> friends, <hi>miſerable comforters,</hi> and that the inuocating of them ſhall be no more regarded, then the ſhouting and crying of the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 27.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hide vs from the face of him that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vpon the Throne, and from the voice of the Lambe.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label>) But how ſhall the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vnfaithfull bee able to ſpeake theſe words, when as they neuer knew Chriſt ſitting in his Throne, nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood him to be the Lamb of God, that <hi>taketh away the ſinnes of the World?</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> told the Iewes, that through ignorance they did crucifie Chriſt, <hi>as did alſo their Gouernours, Acts</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 17. for had they knowne, they would neuer <hi>haue crucified the Lord of glory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> I will not inſiſt vpon any curious diſtinction, either of Logicians, or Schole diuines concerning ignorance. In briefe I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere thus, that the wicked out of the horror, and helliſh deſpaire of a diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted conſcience, partly by reaſon of that imminent danger without them, &amp; the guilt of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience within them, they ſhall be compeld to acknowledge
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19157:15"/>
Chriſt to bee that Incarnated <hi>Word of truth,</hi> ſent out of the boſome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to be that <hi>Lambe of God ſlaine</hi> for as many as beleeue: then they ſhall ſee, know, &amp; be made to acknowledge him; though in their life time they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his ſacred Deitie into queſtion, yet then ſhal they acknowledge him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion. As <hi>Pharaoh</hi> at the firſt anſwered <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> intreating him from the <hi>Lord,</hi> to let the children of Iſrael goe, that they <hi>may celebrate a feaſt to the Lord in the wilderneſſe.</hi> Quis eſt Deus, <hi>Who is the Lord?</hi> as though he had thought (belike) that there had bin no God, as Atheiſts ſay in their heart, There is no God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1. or that he himſelfe had beene God onely, <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.2. yet afterward hee learned a new leſſon, being inſtructed by diuers ſorts of afflictions, which were as ſo many Sermons to conuict and conuince him of Atheiſme, and was compelled to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God, to be the Authour of them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 8. and he only to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. So ſhall the wicked at that day, howſoeuer at this day they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19157:16"/>
doe ſcorne, deride, and not beleeue in Chriſt to be Ieſus, a Meſſias, a Sauiour, but perſecute him in his members, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.4. when they ſee the truth of propheſies fulfilled, the deſtruction at hand, their owne diſmall deſolation drawing neer, then ſhall they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be the <hi>Sonne of God,</hi> the <hi>Sauiour</hi> of the world, the <hi>Redeemer of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the great day of his wrath is come.</hi>] <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Iude <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the great day</hi>: where we may note the <hi>vniuerſality of it</hi>; all the dayes of iudgement going before, were but <hi>types</hi> and <hi>figures,</hi> but <hi>Epitomes</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends of <hi>that day, that great day, that is to come</hi>; the drowning of the old world was a <hi>great day,</hi> the burning of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> a <hi>great day,</hi> the ranſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> a <hi>great day</hi>; yet all theſe together will not expreſſe and ſhew forth the leaſt part of that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully incomparable <hi>great day,</hi> that is to come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And who can ſtand?</hi>) It is a Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor drawne from thoſe, that whiles ſome eminent danger hangeth ouer
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19157:16"/>
their heads, cannot looke vp, but ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily they flie away, vntill they are out of breath, their ſpirits ſpent, &amp; ſo they fall groueling to the ground; ſo ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>mens hearts ſhall faile them for feare, and for looking after thoſe things that ſhall come to the world, Luke</hi> 21.16. The cauſe of this their fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is not only the fearefull apparitions of heauen, as preſages and prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of their diſmall doome, but <hi>Erynnis conſcientiae,</hi> as <hi>Melancthon</hi> cals it, the ſting of conſcience, like a fiend of hell, dogs and driues them; for the <hi>wicked flie when none purſueth them,</hi> Pro. 28.1. They therefore are ſaid to ſtand, that are not terrified &amp; appaled, which are not caſt downe, neither in body nor minde, but doe confidently expect and wait their Maſters comming; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was our Sauiours counſaile vnto his Diſciples, and in them vnto his whole Church, hauing forewarned them that he would come vpon them, at a time, that <hi>they wote not of,</hi> as <hi>trauell vpon a woman,</hi> as <hi>a thiefe in the night,</hi> he doth fore-arme them too, by willing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19157:17"/>
them to be frequent in watching, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent in prayer; <hi>Watch therefore, &amp; pray continually, that you may be counted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to eſcape all theſe things that ſhall come to paſſe, and that you may bee able to ſtand before the Sonne of man,</hi> Luke 21.36.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing <hi>Analyſed</hi> the whole Chapter, diuided my Text, and expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the wordes, I draw forth this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall doctrine, and it flowes naturall, of its owne accord, without any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſtrayning, or iniury vnto the Text: this is the doctrine:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Doct.</note> that <hi>the ſtate and condition of the wicked is full of horror at the day of iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is proued by phraſes of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Firſt, It is called the Lords day, the day of the Lord, intimating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that as the wicked haue had their day, the terme of their life, wherein they dare as boldly to commit ſinne, as if they ſhould neuer come to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and as the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <hi>putting farre off the euill day, and approching to the ſeat of iniquity,</hi> Amos 6.3. ſo likewiſe the <hi>Lord</hi> will haue his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19157:17"/>
               <hi>day</hi>: and <hi>theſe are the dayes of vengeance,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 21. <hi>v.</hi> 22. wherein the Lord will execute the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerity of his wrath, vpon ſinne and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is called the day of <hi>wrath</hi>; now, the <hi>wrath</hi> of a <hi>King is the meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death,</hi> how much more the <hi>wrath</hi> of the Lord of Hoſts, the breath of whoſe noſtrils kindleth that euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly burning <hi>Tophet,</hi> and his <hi>wrath</hi> abideth for euer vpon the children of diſobedience, in that burning Lake of hell fire; for they that haue iuſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked the Lord vnto <hi>wrath</hi> in this their life time, <hi>by fornication, by vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by inordinate affection, by euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, by couetouſneſſe, which is Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, by wrath, by anger, by maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by curſed and filthy ſpeaking, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſ.</hi> 3.5.8. ſhall be ſure to finde the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence and their reward; wrath for wrath, the very fruit of their owne fruitleſſe works, <hi>for, for theſe things ſake the wrath of God commeth vpon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of diſobedience, Coloſ.</hi> 3.6. tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally by manifeſt iudgements of his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19157:18"/>
               <hi>wrath,</hi> and eternally in hell, where his <hi>wrath</hi> abideth for euer and for euer; in that dungeon of <hi>Dogs,</hi> that is, among the wicked, whoſe eſtate is worſe then a Dogs; as namely, <hi>Inchanters, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, Murtherers, Idolaters, and whoſoeuer loueth or maketh lyes,</hi> Reuel. 22.15.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, our Sauiour Chriſt ſpeaking of that day, ſaith; that it ſhould come vpon the world, as trauell vpon a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with child: which is not onely to be vnderſtood of the vncertainty of it when it will come, (yet as ſure will it come as trauell vpon a woman with child:) but the ſimilitude holds true in another ſenſe; that as <hi>a woman with child drawing neere to her trauell, is in ſorrow, and cryeth in her paines,</hi> Iſay 26.17. (a puniſhment peculiar to that ſex, by reaſon of our firſt Parents tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16.) ſhe doth oftentimes ſend foorth bitter ſighes, and ſobbes, grieuous grones, &amp; lamentable cryes, vncertayne whether her iſſue will bee a <hi>Beniamin,</hi> the ſonne of her right hand, or a <hi>Benoni,</hi> the ſonne of her ſorrow &amp;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19157:18"/>
death, yet ſtill doth ſhee <hi>lift vp her eyes vnto the Hils, from whence commeth her helpe</hi>; ſo the wicked ſhall lift vp their eyes vnto the Hils, for they ſhall cry vnto the Hils for helpe, vnto the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes for ſuccour, and vnto the Rocks for ſafety, yet they ſhall receiue none from neither. Me thinkes, I heare not onely <hi>Ieroms</hi> Trumpet ſounding in mine <note n="*" place="margin">Surgite mortui, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite ad iudicium.</note> eares; but a horrible howling of a promiſcuous multitude; <hi>a greater mourning, weeping, and lamentation was neuer heard in Rama, Matt.</hi> 2.18. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents weeping for their children, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for their parents; the husband for the wife, the wife for the husband; yet can they not helpe one another, but as they haue beene companions in ſin, ſo ſhal they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions in torments, and ſuch torments that are matchleſſe, farre beyond the paynes of women, for her paynes end, either with a happy birth, or with as happy a buriall; for <hi>better is the day of death, then the day wherein we are borne:</hi> but the paines of the wicked are endles, eaſeleſſe, reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſſe, and as they haue conceiued ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19157:19"/>
ſo ſhall they receiue the fruit thereof.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>S. Iohn</hi> deſcribing the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſtate &amp; condition of the Church vnder Antichriſt, doth very liuely ſet forth the deſperate eſtate and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition of the wicked, at the day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: <hi>they ſhall ſeeke for death in thoſe dayes, and ſhall not finde it, they ſhall deſire to dye, and death ſhall flye from them, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. l. <hi>3.</hi> Ethic.</note> 9.6. Death, according to the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, is of all terribles the moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, and vnto the naturall man it is euen death to remember death, yet full glad would the wicked bee, if they might returne to their graue againe, &amp; neuer heare and feele that dreadfull doome of diuine iuſtice, denounced and inflicted vpon them, at that laſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting iudgement in Hell,<note place="margin">Gregor. Moral.</note> 
               <hi>Vbi erit miſeris mors ſine morte, finis ſine fine, defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus ſine defectu, quia mors ibi ſemper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit, &amp; deficere neſcit</hi>; where the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhal be euer burning, and yet neuer conſume; euer dying, and yet neuer dead; for there is death without a death, an end without an end, becauſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19157:19"/>
death alwayes begins, and knowes not how to end. If <hi>Death be acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the aged, whoſe ſtrength faileth, and are vexed with all kinde of euill things, Eccleſ.</hi> 41. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. and are depriued of all kinde of good, belonging vnto a naturall life, as of <hi>Seeing, Hearing, Taſting, Smelling, Feeling,</hi> how much more welcome would Death bee vnto the wicked at that dreadfull day of iudgement, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are baniſhed out of the ſociety of Saints, excluded out of heauen, ſent packing to hell, where their <hi>ſight</hi> ſhall bee afflicted with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable darkneſſe, and vgly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, their <hi>ſmelling</hi> with noiſome ſtinks, their <hi>taſte</hi> with rauenous hunger and bitterneſſe of gall, their <hi>hearing</hi> with hideous and horrible cryes, their <hi>fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> with intolerable fire; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, death ſhall bee far from them, Hell muſt be their habitation, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils their companions, and they muſt embrace flames of fire in their armes, for their inheritance.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Prophet <hi>Malachie</hi> in his fourth Chapter, verſ. 1. prophecying of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19157:20"/>
the terrible day of the Lords comming, compares and likens it to an <hi>Ouen: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the day commeth, that ſhall burne as an Ouen, and all the proud, yea, and all that doe wickedly ſhall be ſtubble, and the day that commeth ſhall burne them vp, ſo that there ſhall not bee left neither roote nor branch.</hi> The Ouen whereinto the three Children were caſt, was excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding fearefull, being made ſeuen times more hotte, then it was wont to bee, and <hi>yet not an haire of their head was burnt, nor their coates changed, nor any ſmell of fire came vpon them, Dan.</hi> 3.27. But how dreadfull ſhall this fornace of hell be, being ſo infinitely hotter then that was! Our Sauiour Chriſt <hi>calls it a fornace of fire, Mat.</hi> 13.42.50. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Diuine, <hi>a lake of fire and brimſtone, Reuel.</hi> 21.8. The Apoſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, <hi>a deuouring fire, Heb.</hi> 10.27. an <hi>vnquenchable fire, Matth.</hi> 3.12. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>all vnbeleeuers, and the abominable, and murtherers, and whoremongers, and ſorcerers, and all lyars, the proud, and all that doe wickedly, ſhall be fuell: for they ſhal be bound in ſheaues and bundles,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19157:20"/>
our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.30. The Adulterer and the Adultereſſe in one bundle, the Drunkard and the Glutton in another bundle, the Couetous and Extortioner in another bundle, the Vſurer and the Oppreſſor in another bundle, the Swearer and the falſe Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer in another bundle, the Contemners of God and Breakers of his Sabbaths in another bundle, and ſhall bee caſt as faggots and fire-brands into this <hi>Ouen, into this fornace, into this lake of brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, into this deuouring and vnquencha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fire; vbi nec tortores deficient, nec tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti miſeri morientur,</hi> where their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall neuer ceaſe, but there ſhal be torments alwaies for the body, and body alwaies for the torments, world without end.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Our Sauiour Chriſt ſetting forth the deſperate eſtate, and condition of of the wicked at that day, ſaith,<note place="margin">Anxietas gentium in conſilij in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opia, Bez. vſque ad deſperatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, Ierom.</note> that there ſhall be diſtreſſe of nations with perplexitie, <hi>Luke</hi> 21. the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> properly belongs vnto cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues and priſoners, that are ſo ſhut vp in dungeons, or cloſe priſoners, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19157:21"/>
brought vnto ſuch a doubtfull and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſtrait, that there is no meanes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for them to get out:<note place="margin">Regiomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taenus in Bruſſia.</note> or alluding vnto ſome kind of priſons, wherein the partie impriſoned is in ſuch a perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that he can neither ſit, ſtand vpright, nor lye vpon the ground: ſuch is the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the wicked at that day; they are in ſuch a ſtrait, in ſuch a perplexitie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto deſperation, that they ſee no meanes poſſible to eſcape the hand of God. If they looke vpward, there is <hi>Index iratus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg.</note> an angry Iudge; if they looke downeward, there is <hi>horrendum inferni chaos,</hi> the horrible wide gaping mouth of hell; if they looke on the one ſide of them, there are <hi>peccata accuſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> their ſinnes accuſing them, if they looke on the other ſide of them, there are <hi>infinita daemonia ad ſupplicium tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hentia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſelm.</note> a <hi>Legion</hi> of deuils ready to draw them to execution; if they looke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, there is <hi>mundus ardens,</hi> a world of fire burning round about them, ready to deuoure them; if they looke within them, there is <hi>conſcientia vrens,</hi> a griping conſcience, the <hi>worme
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19157:21"/>
that neuer dieth; Latere erit impoſſibile,</hi> to lye hid it wil be impoſſible, <hi>apparere erit intolerabile, to goe forward 'twill be intolerable.</hi> No maruell therefore though at the worlds end, men bee at their wits end, <hi>Luke.</hi> 21.26. <hi>Hinc illae lachrimae,</hi> hence ariſe <hi>Eſaus</hi> teares, to no end nor purpoſe; <hi>Hinc eiulatuum anguſtiae,</hi> hence ariſeth a horrible how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, <hi>when all the wicked ſhall be gathered together as priſoners in the pit, and ſhal be ſhut vp inpriſon, Iſaiah</hi> 23, 22. to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned at the barre of Gods tribunall, and to receiue according to thoſe things, which they haue done in the fleſh, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. Then <hi>tribulation and anguiſh,</hi> nay, deſperation <hi>ſhal be vpon the ſoule of euery one that doth euil, Rom.</hi> 2.9. then ſhall the wicked not bee able to ſtand; becauſe they haue walked in the counſell of the wicked, and ſtood too long <hi>in the way of ſinners, Pſa.</hi> 1.1. They cannot ſit; becauſe they haue been too long ſit faſt in ſin, and <hi>Moablike,</hi> haue weltred in the dregges of their owne impieties, or as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh, haue ſit <hi>too long in the ſeate of the ſcorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:19157:22"/>
They cannot lye along vpon the ground, becauſe they haue had a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent portion of reſt already, they haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at caſe all their life long, and done nothing but ſtretch themſelues vpon their beds of downe, ſpent their daies in chambering and wantonnes, taking thought for the fleſh, to fulfill the luſt thereof; and like the Iſraelites, ſit downe to eate and drinke, and ſo riſe vp to play: but now their ioy ſhall be turned into heauineſſe, their mirth into mourning, their ſinging into ſighing, their caſe and reſt into caſeleſſe paines, and reſtleſſe torments, <hi>for the wicked ſhall be turned into hell, and ſo ſhal al they that doe forget God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If wee looke backe againe vnto the Text, the Parent of my doctrine, wee ſhall finde, that it will yeeld much ſtrength to the confirmation of this truth; then ſhall the <hi>Kings of the earth, and great men, and rich men, &amp;c.</hi> They that in their life time haue beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to controle whole Kingdoms with their countenance, and chaſe before them millions of men, ſhal be compeld
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19157:22"/>
to ſeeke ſuch weak ſhelters, ſuch boot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe refuges, as to hide themſelues <hi>in dennes,</hi> creepe into the <hi>craggie rockes,</hi> and hollow vaults of the earth, as though that the infinitely-diſcerning eye of <hi>Almighty God</hi> could not finde them out: though they could goe downe into the very depth of the ſea, or center of the earth, whither can they goe or clime from the al-diſcerning eie of Almightie God? though in their life time they <hi>thinke, that they ſhall neuer be remooued,</hi> but are as ſeemingly ſafe as <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> or as ſecure from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger as Edom, though now <hi>their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe reacheth vnto heauen, and their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion to the ends of the earth, Dan.</hi> 4.19 though now <hi>they build themſelues ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly houſes, for the honour of their Maieſty, verſ.</hi> 27. <hi>Though now they ſeeme to dwell in the clefts of the rocks,</hi> ſecure and farre inough remote out of danger; moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aloft <hi>like Eagles in the aire, making their neſt among the Starres, Obad. v.</hi> 3. as though no danger <hi>ſhould euer come nigh their dwellings.</hi> Yet Kings with their Armies then ſhall flie, and be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19157:23"/>
and yet cannot flie from the preſence of God, nor from beyond the reach of his arme. Thus you ſee, that the truth of this doctrine is confirmed by many proofes, that the eſtate and condition of the wicked is full of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, at the dreadfull day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label>
               <note place="margin">Ob ſignorum multitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note>Now the reaſons of this doctrine are many: the firſt is this, by reaſon of the manifold ſignes, and fearefull appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both in heauen and earth, which will ſtrike an horror, dread and ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zedneſſe into the hearts of the wicked: Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> deſcribes them thus; the <hi>Sunne ſhall bee darkened, and the Moone ſhall not giue her light, the Stars ſhall fall from heauen, and the Powers of heauen ſhall be ſhaken, Mat.</hi> 24.29. The words are to be vnderſtood not meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically, but properly of the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the works of nature; as adiuncts, circumſtances, and fearefull preſages of that diſmall day; when the <hi>Sunne</hi> ſhall not ſtand ſtill only, as at the prayer of <hi>Ioſuah, Ioſ.</hi> 10.12. neither ſhall it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goe backward ten degrees, as vpon
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19157:23"/>
               <hi>Ahaz</hi> Diall, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.8. but it ſhall be as <hi>blacke as a ſackcloth of haire, Reuel.</hi> 6.12. We reade, that there was an exceeding great darkneſſe of the Sunne at our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours Paſſion throughout all the land, <hi>and many bodies of the Saints which ſlept, aroſe, Matth.</hi> 27.52. How fearefull then, and how wonderfull ſhall the comming of Chriſt vnto Iudgement be, when the Sunne, the Moone, and the Starres, and all the powerfull influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of heauen, ſhal grow blacke, duſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie, and vtterly be obſcured? when all the dead, Saints, and ſinners, great and ſmall, both in Sea and land, ſhall come forth of their graues, whereof the firſt was a type and figure,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.31</note> when the Lord himſelfe ſhall deſcend from heauen with a ſhoute, and with the <hi>voice of the Archangell, and with the trumpet of God,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16. Saint <hi>Luke</hi> likewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the circumſtances of that day thus, <hi>There ſhall be ſignes in the Sunne, and in the Moone, and in the Starres, the Sea, and the waters ſhal roare, mens harts ſhall faile them for feare, and for looking after theſe things that ſhall come vpon
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19157:24"/>
the world, Luk.</hi> 21. <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. An Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake of it ſelfe is very fearefull; as threatning the ruines of Citties, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding the ſubuerſion of many ſtately buildings, &amp; ſhaking the very founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Kings Palaces; and the inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of waters hath beene very ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, as our Weſterne parts can very well witneſſe; when men euen wiſht for <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke againe, and ſought the higheſt places for refuge, againſt the mercileſſe waues of the Sea; ſome climbing the clifts of craggy rockes, ſome ſteeples, ſome the tops of houſes, ſome trees, ſome floated vpon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, like <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; his companions; many were drowned. But now when the Seas ſhall roare, Rockes ſhall rent, Mountaines ſhake and ſhiuer, and the glorious Heauens become darke and dusky: how ſhall the hearts of men be appaled with dread and terrour to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſame: and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, theſe things <hi>are but the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of ſorrowes,</hi> ſaith our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, but a Preamble, but a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em, but a Prologue to the Tragedy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:19157:24"/>I am not ignorant but that the darkning of the Sunne, the Moone, and the Starres in the holy Scripture, may ſometimes bee taken for ſome kind of calamity ready to fall vpon ſome particular Kingdome; and that theſe ſignes doe not alway denotate properly the laſt day of Iudgement: but may be referd to ſome other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular times of iudgement; as the great ouerthrow of the Babyloniſh King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13. or the laſt totall and finall deſtruction of the Iewes by the Romanes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. or that celeſtiall and truely Diuine victory of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the Great, againſt <hi>Maxentius</hi> and the Romane Gouernours; in the which the great power of almighty God, miraculouſly ſhone from heauen, in reuenging the precious bloud of the bleſſed Martyrs. So the Wiſe-man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting vs to thinke on God in youth, and not to deferre repentance vntill we be old; drawes one of his motiues and arguments to induce vs thereunto <hi>ab incommodo,</hi> from the manifold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences and impediments ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19157:25"/>
old age, that will hinder vs from the true performance of ſo waighty a worke: <hi>Repent,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and turne to God while the Sun is not darke, nor the Moone, nor the Starres, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.2. that is, before old age approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, when thou ſhalt haue no more pleaſure in thy dayes, then if thou wert ſhut vp in a darke dungeon, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard of the comfort and benefit of thoſe great and glorious lights of Heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond reaſon, <hi>Why the ſtate and condition of the wicked is full of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour at the day of Iudgement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob Iudicis, Maieſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</note> is, <hi>the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty of the Iudge,</hi> the beholding of whoſe countenance, ſo full of glory and maieſty, ſhall poſſeſſe the hearts of the wicked with amazement and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. Now the Iudge at this great Aſſiſe and generall Audit, is Chriſt himſelfe; he that once ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the iudgement ſeat of <hi>Pontius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> to receiue his ſentence, ſhall now ſummon <hi>Pontius Piliate,</hi> and all the Potentates of the earth vnto his Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, to receiue their dreadful doome.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19157:25"/>
That Chriſt is the ſole Iudge at the laſt day; they are his owne words. <hi>The Father iudgeth no man but hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all iudgement vnto the Sonne, Iohn</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 22. <hi>And hath committed vnto him all power and authority to execute iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe he is the Sonne of man,</hi> v. 27. Becauſe hee is the Sonne of man; and this cauſe yeelds vs comfort, elſe were we in a miſerable caſe, hee doth partake of our nature; and therefore is pittifull, compaſſionate: yea, farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond humane reach or reaſon; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles likewiſe were commanded to teſtifie this truth, and to preach this point; that Chriſt is ordained by God, to bee Iudge of the quicke and dead, <hi>Act.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 42. So likewiſe in the 17. <hi>Act.</hi> 31. <hi>Paul</hi> preaching to the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> preſſeth repentance; and the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument which he vſeth to prouoke them thereunto, is the conſideration of the day of Iudgement; when God will <hi>iudge the world in righteouſneſſe by that man,</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſt whom hee hath ordained.</hi> So likewiſe the Apoſtle in the ſecond to the <hi>Romanes, ver.</hi> 16. <hi>God
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19157:26"/>
ſhall iudge the ſecrets of men by Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And in the ſecond to <hi>Timothy, c.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Ieſus Chriſt ſhall iudge the quicke and dead at his appearing.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is manifeſt, that neither the Saints nor the Angels, not God himſelfe: but <hi>mediante Chriſto,</hi> by Chriſt, into whoſe hands hee hath reſigned all power and authority, ſhal iudge all the world at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>Whereunto if any obiect the words of the Apoſtle, in the firſt to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> the 6. <hi>c. v.</hi> 2.3. <hi>The Saints ſhall iudge the world, and not onely the world, but the Angels too:</hi> I anſwere, that there is ſuch a narrow band and ſtrict vnion, betwixt Chriſt and the Saints, that they make one body: ſo that which is granted vnto the head, is not denied vnto the body: Chriſt as the chiefe principall vpon that Bench, doth pronounce that ſentence already reuealed vnto vs in the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. <hi>v.</hi> 41. and the Saints as witneſſes, ſhall ſubſcribe vnto that ſentence, and triumph at the iuſt condemnation of the wicked. This is manifeſt by the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19157:26"/>
mouth of our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Ye which haue followed me in the regeneration, ſhal ſit vpon twelue Thrones, and iudge the twelue tribes of Iſrael, Matth.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 28. or as ſome of the Fathers doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the place,<note place="margin">Amb. Chry. in hunc lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> 
               <hi>The Saints ſhall iudge the world: Quia exemplo fidei perfidiam mundi damnabunt,</hi> as our Sauiour ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the Niniuites, and of the Queen of the South; that they ſhould riſe vp againſt the Iewes to condemne them at the day of Iudgement, that is, by the example of their faith, they ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them of infidelity. Thus <hi>Noah</hi> is ſaid, by preparing the Arke, to ſaue him and his poſterity from the generall Deluge of water, <hi>to condemne the world of infidelity,</hi> who would not beleeue at the preaching of <hi>Noah,</hi> that the world ſhould bee deſtroyed with water, as many Atheiſts and Epicures now a dayes, at our preaching will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that the world ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with fire, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. and vnto this <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith well;<note place="margin">Orig. Hom. in Numb.</note> 
               <hi>Non Paulus ipſe ſed opus Pauli, quod faciebat in Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelio, iudicabit mundum</hi>: So that to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19157:27"/>
conclude, the Faith, the Life, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, the Death of the Saints, for the teſtimony of the truth, ſhal condemne the wicked at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is ſaid, <hi>the Saints ſhall iudge the Angels</hi> (leauing Saint <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> opinion,<note place="margin">In hunc locum.</note> who would by <hi>Angels</hi> to bee vnderſtood <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who are called <hi>Angels, Apoc.</hi> 2.1. and ſo the Biſhops of the Churches of Aſia are called <hi>Angels</hi>) wee may ſafely and moſt truly vnderſtand the ſpirituall powers, <hi>Angels</hi> that fell from their firſt eſtate, and ſo are become reprobate Deuils: theſe curſed crue, I ſay, <hi>that are reſerued in euerlaſting chaines vnder darknes, vnto the iudgement of the great day, Iude</hi> 6. ſhall yeeld themſelues ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto the cenſure and ſentence of the Saints.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing ſhewed, who that <hi>Iudge</hi> ſhall be, it remaines that I ſpeake of his <hi>Maieſty,</hi> as farre as it is reuealed vnto vs in his word. As a <hi>King</hi> prouiding for warre, maketh choiſe of ſuch men, as may beſt ſerue to ſet forth the royalty of a King, and for their valour able to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19157:27"/>
encounter with the beſt of his approch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enemies: So Chriſt, when he comes <hi>riding vpon the cloudes,</hi> to encounter with the inhabitants of the earth, for ſinne, he will come <hi>in power and great glory, Luke</hi> 21.27. and this his power doth conſiſt in a glorious multitude of heauenly attendants; not ſilly Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as in the dayes of his infirmity, but a glorious troupe of holy <hi>Saints</hi> and bleſſed <hi>Angels,</hi> as conſorting with him at the appearing of his Maieſty. <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Iude <hi>14</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>he commeth,</hi> ſaith S. Iude, <hi>with thouſand of his Saints, to giue iudgement against all men, and to rebuke all the vngodly</hi>; and as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall come with his many <hi>Saints,</hi> ſo ſhall he appeare with his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite troupe and traine of Angels. <hi>For thouſand thouſands ſhall miniſter vnto him, and ten thouſand thouſands ſhall ſtand before him, yea he ſhall come with all his holy Angels, Dan.</hi> 7.10. which is to be vnderſtood of Chriſt, &amp; his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Iudgement: for in the ninth <hi>verſe</hi> mention is made of the Ancient of dayes, ſitting downe vpon his Throne; that is, <hi>God the Father</hi>: and in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19157:28"/>
the thirteenth <hi>verſe</hi> it is added, that the <hi>Sonne of man approched vnto the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of daies, which gaue vnto him power, honor and a Kingdome:</hi> that is, Chriſt, into whoſe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, God the Father hath giuen power and authority of iudging the quick and the dead, at the laſt day. Now if <hi>Iehoram</hi> was halfe aſtoniſhed at the furious marching of <hi>Iehu</hi> &amp; his company, &amp; therefore ſent forth horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to meet him, and enquire whether it <hi>were peace or no,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 9.16. how much more will it ſtrike the wicked with amazement, and dreadfull aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, when they ſhall ſee Chriſt comming againſt them with millions of Saints, and Legions of Angels, and no conditions of peace will be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, <hi>but he will bruiſe them with a rod of iron, and breake them in peeces like a Potters Veſſel? Pſal.</hi> 2.9. And hee will not onely come <hi>in power,</hi> but <hi>in glory, in great glory</hi>: and no maruaile, for the Father hath glorified him, &amp; will glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him againe, when he hath gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together the Elect, from the foure corners of the earth, and both ſhall
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19157:28"/>
make one glorious body in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſo full of glory, where their Hymnes and Haleluiahs ſhal be glory, and honor, &amp;c. for euer and for euer. It is the obſeruation of ſome vpon the 24. of <hi>Matth.</hi> that the Sunne ſhall bee darkned,<note place="margin">Ferus Spangin.</note> and the Moone ſhall not giue her light, at the bright ſhining &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious appearing of Chriſt Ieſus. As greater lights are wont to obſcure the leſſer (as the bright beames of the Sun, the glimmering light of a Candle) ſo the exceeding brightneſſe and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent glory of Chriſt, at his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ſhall darken all thoſe glorious lamps and lights of heauen, whoſe ſweet influence, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable beames wee now enioy day by day. To this S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Diuine alludeth.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>He had in his right hand ſeuen ſtarres, and out of his mouth went a ſharp two-edged ſword, and his face ſhone as the Sunne ſhineth in his ſtrength, Reuel.</hi> 1.16. <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſetting forth the glory of his comming, ſaith, <hi>He ſhall come in flaming fire, with the ſound of an Archangell: he ſhall come in the cloudes, and ride vpon the wings of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19157:29"/>
the winde.</hi> Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> thus; <hi>Then ſhall he ſit vpon a Throne of glory, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him ſhall bee gathered all Nations, Matth.</hi> 24.31. The gloriouſneſſe of which <hi>Throne Daniel</hi> deſcribeth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>His Throne was like a fiery flame, and the wheeles like burning fire,</hi> Dan. 7.6. And if the Earth and the Sea doe reele too and fro, ſtart and ſtagger, <hi>and flye away<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Reuel.</hi> 20.11. as not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to behold the glory, nor endure the face of this approching Iudge: how much leſſe ſhall the wicked bee able to ſtand, which are <hi>inutile terrae pondus,</hi> the very chaffe, the droſſe, the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of the earth, and therefore no maruaile, though <hi>they goe into the holes of the Rocks, and into the Caues of the earth, from before the feare of the Lord, and from the glory of his Maieſty, when he ſhall ariſe to deſtroy the earth,</hi> Iſaiah 2.19. <hi>Mallent enim impij eſſe in inferno, quàm videre faciem irati Iudicis.</hi> The wicked had rather be throwne downe to hell, where is vtter darkeneſſe, then endure the glorious preſence of ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Iudge. If <hi>S. Iohn</hi> the bleſſed <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelator</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:19157:29"/>
of heauens ſecrets, fell at the <hi>feet of Chriſt as dead, when he beheld him, Reu.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 17. If <hi>Moſes</hi> that man of God, could not indure the face of God: but couered his eyes with a vaile: If the <hi>Seraphins</hi> that ſtand about the Throne of God, couer their <hi>faces with two of their wings,</hi> as not being able to behold the glorious Maieſty of God, <hi>how ſhall the Maieſty of this our great God, euer our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, Tit.</hi> 2.13. daunt the hearts of the wicked at his appearing, euen more then can be expreſſed?</p>
            <p>The third reaſon, why the eſtate and condition of the wicked is ſo full of horrour at the Day of Iudgement, is; by reaſon of the ſtrict account that they muſt render: All men without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny exception, <hi>Adam</hi> and all his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; as many as haue beene dead be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; as many as are then liuing: and <hi>they that are then liuing, ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent them that ſleepe:</hi> I ſay all men, and ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Wee ſhall all appeare before the Iudgement ſeat of Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>Euery one of vs ſhall giue an
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19157:30"/>
account of himſelfe to God, v.</hi> 12. <hi>And euery man ſhall receiue the things which are done in his body, according to that he hath done, whether it bee good or euill,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 10. And not onely all men, but all the <hi>Angels which kept not their firſt eſtate, but left their owne habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>are reſerued in euerlaſting chaines, vnder darkneſſe, vnto the Iudgement of the Great Day, Iude, verſ.</hi> 6. This truth the Deuils themſelues did confirme by their deſperate crying out, fearing their preſent executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnto the which they themſelues know they are reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; <hi>Quid nobis &amp; tibi, What haue we to doe with thee, Ieſus, thou Sonne of God? art thou come to torment vs before the time? Matth.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 29. And this feare is the <hi>chaines</hi> and fetters before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, in the which the Deuils are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacled, vntill they bee brought forth vnto the full execution of the wrath of God in Hell, the place of Deuils, and all the damned.</p>
            <p>And not onely men, and Deuils; but vnreaſonable creatures, the heauen and the earth, and whatſoeuer is contained
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19157:30"/>
within this ſpacious Vniuerſe, ſhall be iudged alſo after their manner at that day. So ſaith Saint <hi>Peter, The heauens and the earth are reſerued vnto fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the day of Iudgement, and of the deſtruction of vngodly men, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens ſhall paſſe away with a noiſe,</hi> that is, they ſhall paſſe away from a mutable condition, vnto an immutable degree of perfection; <hi>The Elements ſhall melt with heat, and the earth with the workes that are therein ſhall bee burnt vp.</hi> Not that the great Fabricke, and glorious workmanſhip of heauen and earth ſhal be burnt, and brought to nothing: for <hi>the earth remaineth for euer, Eccleſ.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>Sed ab ea quae nunc habet ſpecie, per ignem tergetur, ea tamen in ſua natura ſeruatur, Greg. l.</hi> 17. <hi>Moral. c.</hi> 5. They ſhall bee purged of their corruptible qualities, and purified from the filth of their imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as the Sun &amp; Moon ſhall be no more eclipſed, and ſublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary things ſhall be no more ſubiect to generation and corruption: but as the gold caſt into the fire, is purged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the droſſe, whereby it becomes a refined
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19157:31"/>
ſubſtance; ſo the heauens and the earth ſhall put on, as it were, new appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, adorned with <hi>a new faſhion: for the</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>faſhion of this world paſſeth away,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31. but not the nature and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. <hi>Hierom</hi> prooueth as much by that place, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.26. <hi>The light of the Moone ſhall be as the light of the Sunne, and the light of the Sunne ſhall be ſeuen-fold; non interitum ſignificat priſtinorum, ſed commutationem in melius.</hi> Whereby the holy Ghoſt doth ſignifie, not a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of thoſe lights which were before; but a change into a better. <hi>Caluin</hi> goeth farther, ſaying; that they ſhall bee fellowes with the Saints in that glorious eſtate. And ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Non ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la generum, ſed genera ſingulorum, Ordi. Gloſs. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Creature</hi> (that is the world) <hi>ſhall be deliuered from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of corruption, into the glorious liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Sonnes of God, Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 21. So <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. there is promiſed a <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Non ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la generum, ſed genera ſingulorum, Ordi. Gloſs. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration of all things</hi>; So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. <hi>The heauens ſhall all wax old as doth a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and they ſhall be changed,</hi> that is, into a better forme and faſhion. So S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw a new <hi>Heauen, and a new
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19157:31"/>
earth, Apo.</hi> 21.1. So S. <hi>Peter, We looke for a new heauen, and a new earth, according to his promiſe, &amp;c. v.</hi> 13. Hence is it, that the perpetuity of Chriſt his <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Kingdome,</hi> is ſhadowed out vnto vs by the continuance of the Sun and Moone. <hi>His Throne ſhall be as the Sun, Pſal.</hi> 89. <hi>v.</hi> 36.37. and ſhall be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed for euermore as the <hi>Moone, Pſal.</hi> 72. <hi>ve ſ.</hi> 5. Gods children ſhall feare him, ſo long as the <hi>Sunne and Moone indureth, verſ.</hi> 7. And Chriſt his name ſhall indure, <hi>ſo long as the Sunne, verſ.</hi> 17. Therefore it muſt bee granted, that theſe creatures ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, and ſo continue without decay, or corruption; or elſe it muſt muſt bee yeelded, that Chriſts Kingdome muſt haue an end, which may not bee gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But after what manner this inſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſhall be, it is not manifeſted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in the word of God: and to what end they ſhall ſerue, whether as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of Gods glory; it were curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to ſearch or determine, ſufficient is it to know, that they ſhall bee iudged after their kind.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:19157:32"/>But if any ſhould obiect againſt what hath bin ſpoken, as namely, <hi>that al men ſhall giue an account:</hi> The ſixt verſe of the firſt <hi>Pſalme,</hi> the wicked <hi>ſhall not ſtand in Iudgement,</hi> And that of <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.24. <hi>He that beleeueth in him that ſent me, hath euerlaſting life, and ſhall not come into Iudgement.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lombardus ex Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio binos facit ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candorum, alij iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur &amp; pereunt, alij non iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur &amp; pereunt, alij iudicantur &amp; regnant, alij non iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicantur &amp; regnant, Lomb. l. <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>49.</hi>
               </note> Theſe places in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed haue much troubled the Fathers, in ſo much, that <hi>Hillarie</hi> and <hi>Origen</hi> were of opinion, that neither the godly Faithfull, nor the wicked Infidels ſhall be iudged: the one being cleared, the other condemned in their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> thinketh, that the righteous only ſhall come into Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>quia feſtinant innoxij adiudicium,</hi> the righteous they do haſten to Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and long to heare that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſentence pronounced: <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father, &amp;c.</hi> But the places may better be reconciled thus: there is a twofold Iudgement, a Iudgement of <hi>abſolution,</hi> and a Iudgement of <hi>condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> The wicked ſhall not ſtand in that Iudgement, which the righteous ſhall receiue, as namely, to bee quitted
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19157:32"/>
and abſolued. The latter part of the verſe thus expounding the former, <hi>nor the ſinners in the aſſembly of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:</hi> and the righteous ſhall not come into Iudgement, that is, ſhall not bee condemned with the wicked: for they ſhall both be iudged apart, the one at the right hand,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. 25.34.41.</hi> Non iudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur .i. no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur, Irenaeus.</note> the other at the left hand of Chriſt, and ſhall receiue a farre diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent doome, as farre as a curſe differs from a bleſſing, hell from heauen; ſo that the Texts alleaged are thus to bee reconciled; The righteous ſhall not come into Iudgement (that is) into condemnation; the wicked ſhall not ſtand in Iudgement, (that is) they ſhall be conuinced in their owne <hi>conſcience</hi> of the iuſt ſentence, and deſerued con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, that they ſhall not be able to gaine ſay, or contradict.</p>
            <p>Now the ſtrictneſſe of their account will appeare, if wee, conſider how many things they ſhall bee call'd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an account for. Firſt,<note place="margin">De cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus.</note> of the thoughts of our heartes, though neuer ſo ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contriued, though neuer vttered by the tongue, though neuer acted by the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19157:33"/>
hand, yet if there be a deliberate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and free approbation of the will and affections, and a full reſolution to put the ſame in practice, if we had place and fit opportunitie; I ſay, this ſinne of thought ſhall not goe for nought at the day of Iudgement; elſe why ſhould the Lord take notice <hi>of all the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the thoughts of his heart? Geneſ.</hi> 6.5. why ſhould the Lord deſire <hi>ſo much the heart, My ſonne, giue mee thy heart</hi>: but becauſe it is the roote and fountaine, either of good or euill? If it be the ſtorehouſe of good things, and Treaſurie of diuine meditations, it is a Temple meete for God to dwell in: but if it bee a cage of vncleane birds, of euill <hi>thoughts,</hi> it is already poſſeſſed with ſo many <hi>deuils.</hi> If the euil <hi>thoughts</hi> of the heart were not ſinnes, and ſo by a conſequent come to Iudgement: Why ſhould the Lord ſtile himſelfe the <hi>ſearcher of the heart, and trier of the reines,</hi> were it not ſo puniſh? according to the ſaying of the Wiſe man; <hi>There ſhall inquiſition be made for the thoughts of the vngodly, there ſhall not a wicked
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19157:33"/>
thought paſſe in Iudgement, Wiſ.</hi> 1.9. If adultery be a ſinne, and <hi>luſting after a woman,</hi> though it breakes not out into act, <hi>be adulterie, Matth.</hi> 5.28. <hi>And no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer ſhall enter into the Kingdome of Heauen,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.10. then are the thoughts of the heart ſinne, and ſo by a conſequent, they ſhall come to Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſhall preuaile in Iudgement. If manſlaughter be a ſinne, as indeede it is a <hi>crying ſinne</hi>:<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.15</note> 
               <hi>and if he that hateth his brother be a manſlayer,</hi> and no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlayer <hi>ſhall inherit the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, Reuel.</hi> 21.8. then are the thoughts of the heart, ſinne, and they ſhall bee brought foorth to the condemnation of the wicked, at the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Hence is it, that our Sauiour Chriſt ſo ſharpely inueigheth againſt the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> who ſtood ſo much vpon their owne <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> in fulfilling the <hi>Law</hi>; thinking that if they did not violate the Law in act, by killing, or committing adultery, or by any other actuall tranſgreſſion, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Law of God, that they had performed the Law to a haires bredth.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19157:34"/>
But our Sauiour reproouing them and their righteouſneſſe, which they did ſo much extol, that they ſhould not enter into the Kingdome of Heauen, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this their righteouſneſſe, ſheweth, that there was a ſtricter courſe required in performing the Law: for whoſoeuer is angry with his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnaduiſedly, <hi>ſhall bee culpable of iudgement, Matth.</hi> 5.22. The <hi>Law</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth euery inclination to be euill, and the heart doth kill as well as the hand, in will, in wiſh, in deſire: the heart committeth adultery, the heart doth ſteale as well, or rather ill, as the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward members. For if we conſent to thoſe wicked motions ſuggeſted by Satan, (though wee neuer performe them outwardly in act) yet before God wee haue done the ſinne: and if the thought bee truly ſinne, farre greater is that ſinne of act. Yea, the ſinne of thought is not onely a ſinne, but is the very originall, the fountaine, and roote, from whence all other ſinnes do ſpring; and therefore ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>That which goeth into the man, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19157:34"/>
not the man: but thoſe things which come forth from the hart, as euil thoughts, murders adulteries, fornications, thefts, falſe witneſſes, blaſphemies, theſe defile the man, Mat.</hi> 15.19. So that there is not a ſinne, of what nature ſoeuer, great or ſmall, from the leaſt infirmitie to the higheſt blaſphemie, but it had its firſt beginning from the heart: thought is the ſeede of all ſins, and though but a ſpark at the firſt, yet wil it encreaſe into a flame, if it be not repreſſed. For this is ſins gradation, firſt,<note place="margin">Hall. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditat.</note> there is preſented a fit obiect; from the obiect, is raiſed an il ſuggeſtion, ſuggeſtion brings on de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, delight conſent, conſent ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, endeuour practice, practice cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, cuſtome excuſe, excuſe defence, defence obſtinacie, obſtinacy boaſting of ſinne, and boaſting of ſinne a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſenſe; when the cuſtome of ſinne hath taken away the ſenſe of ſinne, and miſerable man is ſold as a bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaue vnto Satan to commit <hi>wickednes, euen with greedines.</hi> And therefore <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> counſel in this kind is very wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be embraced. <hi>Keepe thine heart
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19157:35"/>
with all diligence, for thereout commeth life: If thou keepeſt it not diligently, and warily, thereout will proceed death, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs,</hi> 4.23. As Chriſts aduice vnto the Church is, that the little <note n="*" place="margin">Hereſies.</note> Foxes be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and bee kild whileſt they are but Cubs, (not that they can doe much harme, but if they liue vntill they bee Foxes, they will ſpoile, kill, and make a prey of any thing whatſoeuer:) euen ſo the thoughts of the heart at the firſt, may ſeeme to be but ſmall ſinnes; but if they bee not ſlaine at the firſt, and ſmothered as ſoone as they be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, they will breake forth into actuall tranſgreſſions, and ſo lade the ſoule with ſinne; kill therfore theſe Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trices in the egge, ſlay them whileſt they be but Cubs: Oh, <hi>happie is he that taketh theſe young children, and daſheth their braines againſt the ſtones</hi>: and ſo much the rather, becauſe they are ſinnes, and ſhall come to Iudgement, <hi>for the Lord ſhall iudge the ſecrets of men, Rom.</hi> 2.16.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Inquiſition ſhall not only bee made of the thoughts of the heart,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19157:35"/>
but wee muſt alſo giue an account of the words of the mouth: They are the words of him that is the word of truth; <hi>Of euery idle word that men ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall giue an account thereof at the day of Iudgement, Matth.</hi> 12.36. If a man might be called to an account but for his groſſer ſort of ſinnes, as for his Whoredom, Swearing, Cheating, Stea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Vſuries, Briberies, Extortions, diſhallowing of Sabbaths, and the like; there were ſome hope of ſafety, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, God knowes, there is no hope of the ſaluation of ſuch, without a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and vnfained repentance; which doth conſiſt in an holy confeſſion of their ſinnes; in an hearty ſorrowing for the ſame;<note place="margin">Sermonem otioſum vocat ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, &amp; nullius v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitatis, qui ſc: nihil aedificatie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, vel fructus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor. ex Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in a faithfull reſtitution of that which hee hath taken from any man by falſity and wrong, and in a godly reformation of his forepaſt life: but God will bring into iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, not onely euery ſecret thought, but euery idle word: and who, alas, ſhall be able to anſwere him, <hi>one of a thouſand?</hi> Iob 9.3. Now an idle word is that, which is ſpoken without a fruitfull edification
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19157:36"/>
of the hearers: for our wordes ought not onely to be few, but alſo they muſt be good, and gracious, they muſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoury, and well ſeaſoned with the ſalt of the Sanctuary, and therefore <hi>Iob</hi> cals the eare the taſter of the Word; that as we, in the common foode of our body ſwallow not any thing downe into the ſtomack, but what the pallat approues to be good, and the grinders prepare for digeſtion: ſo the eare will not giue paſſage vnto any word, vnleſſe it relliſh of the Spirit of ſanctification, and bee truely good to the vſe of edifying, and may conuay ſome ſpiritual nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the ſoule: and therefore it is the exhortation of the bleſſed Apoſtle, <hi>Let no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication proceed out of the mouth, but that which is good, to the vſe of edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that it may miniſter grace vnto the hearers, Epheſ.</hi> 4.29. The tongue is the Harbinger of the heart, and the trueſt Ambaſſador, both of the minde and meaning, it will ſoone diſcry and make manifeſt vnto others, what Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men we are, whether we belong vnto the Prouince of Babel, or the Land of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19157:36"/>
Canaan. If wee belong vnto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of Heauen, then our ſpeech is of this Countrey, our language is heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; we are frequent in praiſing of God, in talking of his Word, and in telling forth what great things the Lord hath done vnto our ſoules: as our affections are in heauen, ſo is our talke of heauen, and heauenly things. But if we belong vnto that infernall Kingdome, then is the ſpeech carnall, ſenſuall, diabolicall; then is the tongue exerciſed in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of that Countrey, in ſwearing, falſe-ſwearing, curſing, banning, and blaſpheming: then is our communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuch, as may helpe to aduance the Kingdome of Satan, whereof wee our ſelues are limmes, and whereof hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter without repentance, wee ſhall be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtingly burning, and neuer conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire-brands.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore, if euery man muſt giue-an account of euery idle word, not tending to the edification of himſelfe and others, and of all corrupt and filthy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication, whereby hee hath <hi>grieued the holy Spirit of God, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſ.</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:19157:37"/>
4.30. Tremble then, thou ſwearing and falſe ſwearing tongue, whoſe Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick and Eloquence of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon talke, is an execrable oth, nay, as many othes as wordes: thou that canſt not ſell a penny worth, or a pound weight, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dozens of othes: we haue a world full of ſuch tongues, and becauſe of ſuch kind of tongues the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mournes; Gods heauy iudgements are gone out againſt it: if account muſt bee made of euery idle word, what ſhall become of that tongue that hath pleaded an vniuſt cauſe to the peruerting of Iuſtice, wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the Law, to the vtter vndoing of the fatherleſſe &amp; widdowes? what ſhall become of that tongue, that cannot ſpeake a word, in the defence of the poore, vnleſſe it be well tipt with gold, the oyle that makes euery ioynt to bee nimble, and euery bad cauſe to goe for current? If account muſt bee made of euery idle word, then ſtand amazed, thou vaine and wanton tongue, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and quake when thou heareſt mentioned the terrible day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; thou, whoſe words doe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19157:37"/>
not tend to edification, but to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace the Scripture, the word of God it ſelfe; thou that thinkeſt no ieſt wil goe for current, vnleſſe it be ſeaſoned with the ſalt of the Sanctuary: ſuch is the profaneneſſe of the age in which wee liue, that euery Actor vpon the ſtage, euery profane Swaggerer, and euery mincing Minion ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſpeake a word, but muſt haue a fling and gird at ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified Scripture; aſſuredly, thine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count is the greateſt, thy caſe fearefull, thy iudgement intolerable. Let euery man therefore take heede vnto his waies, that he offend not in his tongue; let him refraine his tongue from euill; let him deſire the Lord to ſet a watch before his lips, that he may not ſpeake his owne wordes, but ſuch as the Lord by his word co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands him to ſpeake; for if our wordes are not ſuch as they ought to be, wee ſhall giue an account for them at the day of Iudgement.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We ſhall not only be called vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an account for our thoughts,<note place="margin">De operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> and wordes, but alſo of our works, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer and whenſoeuer committed,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19157:38"/>
whether by day, or by night; whether in the field, or in the Citie; whether in the City, or in the houſe; whether in the houſe, or in our chamber; whether in our chamber, or in our bed; there is nothing couered, that ſhall not bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed; nothing hid, that ſhall not bee knowne, and made manifeſt, before God, before the Angels, before Saints, before the whole world, at the day of Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: ſo ſaith the bleſſed Apoſtle, <hi>We muſt all appeare before the Iudgement ſeate of Chriſt, and there receiue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our workes,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. God will giue vnto euery man according to his waies, and according to the fruit of his works; they that haue done good, ſhal goe into euerlaſting life, but they that haue done ill, ſhal goe into euerlaſting fire: This, God himſelfe reuealed to <hi>S. Iohn</hi> for truth it ſelfe: I ſaw the dead, great and ſmall, ſtand before God, and they were iudged <hi>according to their workes, Apoc.</hi> 20.12. To this purpoſe ſaith <hi>Auguſt. In quibus actibus quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> homo inuentus fuerit, quando exierit de corpore, in his iudicabitur</hi>; in what ſins
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19157:38"/>
ſoeuer man goes out of the body vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, of the ſame hee ſhall be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged at the day of Iudgement: as the Preacher therefore concludes his Booke; ſo will I conclude this point, <hi>God will bring euery worke vnto Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with euery ſecret thing, whether it be good or euill, Eccleſ.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Neither ſhall we bee onely called vnto an account for our thoughts, our words, and workes: but alſo for our goods and poſſeſſions, how we haue gotten them, how we haue kept them, how wee haue ſpent them; whether we haue gained our goods through o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hurt, building our houſes <hi>like the Moth, Iob</hi> 27. <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. The Moth is made fatte by ſpoyling the booke and barkes wherein they liue; ſo the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous is made rich in deuouring the poore: Of which ſort are theſe, Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, Extortioners, Cheaters, Brokers, and all couetous <hi>Ahabs</hi> whatſoeuer, that ioyne houſe to houſe, land to land, vntil there be no place for the poore to dwell in: For great men muſt render great account, when that great Land-Lord
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19157:39"/>
comes to reckon with them, and biddes them giue an account of their ſteward-ſhip: for they may be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſtewards. Secondly, we ſhall giue an account how wee haue kept them. Indeed wee are but keepers of our wealth, though wee had the world at will:<note place="margin">Amb. l. de Nab. c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cuſtos es tuarum, non Dominus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatum,</hi> Thou art but a keeper, thou art not Lord ouer thy goods and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> 
               <hi>Deus enim diuitiarum ſuarum diſpenſatores eſſe voluit, non Dominos</hi>: God will haue vs diſpenſers and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of our goods, vnto the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and not to bee Lords ouer them our ſelues; and therfore they be goods, <hi>Non quod faciunt bonum, ſed vnde faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as bonum</hi>: not that they make a man good, but becauſe a man by them may doe good, imploying them to the glory of God, &amp; the good of his neighbour, and his owne comfort. Firſt, vnto God, laying out temporall things, for ſpirituall comforts: in maintaining the Preachers, in defending the Goſpell, in repayring his Temples. Secondly, thou muſt lay them out vpon thy neighbor;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19157:39"/>
making friends of thine vnrighteous Mammon, as thy Maſter commands thee, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 9. <hi>Stips pauperum the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurus inopum,</hi> was the word of the good <hi>Emperour Conſtantius,</hi> The rich mans treaſure, is the poore mans ſtock; ſo that he that denies them what they ſtand in need of, denies them their due; of which ſort Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaks of, that haue their preſſes full of gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and their cheſts full of coyne: but their gold and ſiluer is cankered, their garments motheaten, whiles Chriſt himſelfe in the perſon of a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſtands at their doore with an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty belly, and a naked backe, crying for a morſell of bread to put in their belly, or ſome old caſt garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to couer their nakedneſſe, and yet they are ſent away as comfortleſſe and as empty-handed, as euer they came thither. No maruell therefore, though Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſo ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inueigheth againſt rich men, againſt ſuch kinde of keepers of their goods: <hi>Goe to now, ye rich men, weep and howle, for the miſeries that ſhall come vpon you; your riches are corrupted, and your gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19157:40"/>
motheaten, your gold and ſiluer is cankered, and the ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſſe againſt you, and ſhall eate vp your fleſh, as it were fire; ye haue heaped vp treaſure againſt the laſt dayes, Iames</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 1.2.3. Thirdly, he ſhall giue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count how hee hath ſpent them; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon workes of ſuperſtition to the diſhonour of God; or in the vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary quarrels of the Law, to the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance of his neighbour, or in ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them vpon Whores and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, vntill pox and penury bee his end; or in ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe; to the ruinating of his eſtate, danger of ſoule, hurt of body, loſſe of credite, griefe of friends, vndoing of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8.</note> and <hi>ſuch a one is worſe then an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell.</hi> To conclude therfore this point, euery man muſt giue his account vnto God; the King as wel as the Subiects, the Prince as well as the People, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Magiſtrates, Parents and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Maſters and ſeruants, rich and poore, good and bad, and euery tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion from the higheſt blaſphemy, to the leaſt infirmity, muſt be brought
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19157:40"/>
to a ſtrict tryall at the Day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Which is the third reaſon ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauating the fearefull eſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the wicked at the Day of Iudgement.</p>
            <p>The fourth reaſon why the eſtate and condition of the wicked is ſo full of horror at the Day of Iudgement, is, by reaſon of the multitude of witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and accuſers, which ſhall come forth to witneſſe, accuſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them at that Day. As firſt of all, GOD himſelfe aboue them, which knoweth and <hi>ſealeth vp their ſinnes,</hi> as it were <hi>in a bag, Iob</hi> 14.17. And therfore ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> in a caſe of controuerſie that could not bee decided; <hi>My witneſſe is in heauen.</hi> So <hi>Samuel</hi> declaring to the people his integrity, how vprightly he had conuerſt amongſt them; hee takes the Lord to be a witneſſe betwixt him and the people, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 5. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may ſee how fearefull a thing it is, thus to dally with our all-ſeeing and all-knowing God; as to call his ſacred Maieſty, to be a witnes in matters of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to our own knowledge,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19157:41"/>
and the teſtimony of our owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. For aſſuredly the Lord will bee a witneſſe, a ſwift witneſſe; they are the words of his owne mouth: <hi>I will be a ſwift witneſſe againſt the Sorcerers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Adulterers, againſt falſe ſwearers, againſt thoſe that oppreſſe the hireling in his wages, the widdow and the fatherleſſe, and that turne aſide the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from his right, and feare not me, ſaith the Lord of hoſtes, Mal.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort of accuſers are the Deuils, the whole rabble of that infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Kingdome; the common &amp; ſworne aduerſaries to all mankind, and if they dare to accuſe the brethren, the Saints, and ſeruants of God: as hee did that <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>vpright man of God, holy Iob.</hi> Aſſuredly this will bee his practice at that day, he wil bring forth a moſt exact bill of all our ſinnes committed all our life long. <hi>Preſto erit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine, Diabolus ante tribunall Chriſti, &amp; reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabit verba profeſſtonis noſtrae, &amp; obijciet nobis in faciem omnia quae fecimus; in quo die &amp; in quo loco peccauimus, &amp; quae facere debuimus.</hi> The Deuil wil be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19157:41"/>
before the Tribunall of Chriſt, and will recite the words of what wee haue made profeſſion of, and obiect our owne ſinnes to our faces; in what day, and at what place wee did commit them, and all other circumſtances; howſoeuer wee now caſt them behind our backes, then will hee bring them forth before our faces. It behooues vs therfore, to be watchful ouer our owne wayes, conſidering the Deuil watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ouer vs ſo, that hee wil not let paſſe any one of our ſinnes vnregiſtred: but will bring them forth to the confuſion of the wicked; yea if it were poſſible, of the Saints, at the day of Iudgement. The third ſort of accuſers are the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels beſide them. I wil not here main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Origens</hi> opinion, who ſaith, <hi>Vnuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Angelorum aderit, producens illos quibus praefuit, qui teſtimonium prohibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit quot annis circa eum laborauit ad bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num inſtigando, ſed monita eius ſpreuit.</hi> That as euery man hath his particular Angel attending on him, prouoking him to good, protecting him from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill; euery mans particular Angell ſhal
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19157:42"/>
witneſſe againſt the wicked at that day. But farre greater is the royalty of Gods children, they haue gards of Angels, thouſands of Angels doe inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron them about, and defend them from all their foes, though neuer ſo many, neuer ſo mighty; ſometime ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off the fetters in which they are tyed priſoners, and making paſſage for them, by throwing open the dores of the priſon; and as theſe ſwift-win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked meſſengers doe obſerue the wayes of the wicked, whoſe miniſtery they haue abuſed; and as they haue preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to commit ſin in the ſight of the Angels: the Angels being ſpectators and eye-witneſſes to all their actions, ſhall bee produced as ſo many accuſers at the day of Iudgement. Tremble then, thou profane and looſe liuer, that dareſt to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit that in the ſight of the Angels, which thou feareſt to doe in the ſight of little children.</p>
            <p>The fourth ſort of accuſers are the Saints before them, whom they haue deſpiſed, ſcorned, and abuſed in this life, whom they haue accounted as the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19157:42"/>
ſcumme, and the off-ſcowring of all things, men vnworthy to liue, whom they haue had <hi>in deriſion, and a prouerbe of reproch</hi>; as the wicked haue iudged the godly at their pleaſure, ſo the Saints then ſhal iudge the wicked, the world, that is, the company of the wicked: and they that in this life haue been made the foote-ſtooles of the wicked, ſhall then ſit <hi>vpon Thrones, iudging the twelue Tribes of Iſrael, Matth.</hi> 19.28.</p>
            <p>The fifth ſort of witneſſes are the wicked, witneſſing againſt the wicked. <hi>The men of Niniue,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt <hi>ſhall riſe vp with this generation, and ſhall condemne it; the Queene of the South ſhall riſe vp with this generation in the Iudgement, and ſhall condemne it, Matth.</hi> 12.40.41. Tyre and Sydon ſhall witneſſe againſt Corazin and Bethſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, Sodom and Gomorrah againſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaum, <hi>Ephraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſſes, Manaſſes</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt the Sadduces, the Sadduces againſt the Phariſees, the Pope againſt the Turke, the Turke againſt the Pope; and they that know not whether there
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19157:43"/>
bee a holy Ghoſt or no, ſhall witneſſe againſt the formall Proteſtants of our time, who often talke of the Spirit, and yet walk after the fleſh, hauing a ſhew of godlineſſe, and yet denie the power thereof; yea, and not onely ſo, but birds of a feather, ſuch as haue been compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in ſinne, and haue had fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the vnfruitfull workes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhal witnes one againſt another; the Egyptians againſt the Egyptians, the ſwearer againſt the ſwearer, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioner againſt the Extortioner, the Vſurer againſt the Vſurer, the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard againſt the Drunkard, and they that haue ſlept in the ſame bed of ſin, the Adulterer againſt the Adultereſſe, one wicked wretch ſhal witnes againſt onother at the day of Iudgement. And what know we, but that the Satyrs of Virginia may witneſſe againſt many ſeeming Saints in England at that day? they vnto whom the light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell hath not dawned as yet, but are nuzled in darkneſſe, bred in blindneſſe, and led along in ignorance, ſhal doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe witneſſe againſt many of vs, that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19157:43"/>
liue vnder the ſound of the Word, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying the free paſſage of the Goſpell, the pure preaching of the Word of God <hi>in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon,</hi> that haue had ſo many Sermons of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that haue had ſo many threats of Gods Iudgements denounced againſt vs; and yet wee perſeuere in the ſame ſinnes which wee finde condemed by the Word; <hi>for where grace is moſt plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, there ſin is moſt ſinful</hi>: doubtleſſe, the Heathens, Pagans, and Infidels, Whores and Harlots, ſhall enter into the Kingdome of Heauen, before ſuch, as turne the grace of God into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe.</p>
            <p>Neither ſhall the wicked onely one witneſſe againſt another, but they ſhal all witnes againſt themſelues. Out of the helliſh horror of a diſtracting conſcience, they ſhall witneſſe againſt themſelues, and pronounce themſelues guiltie of euerlaſting condemnation: for when the Ancient of daies ſhall ſit downe vpon his white Throne, before whom Heauen and Earth fled away, then ſhall the Bookes be opened; and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19157:44"/>
the Bookes are two, the Booke of the Law, and the Book of thine owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: The Law will pleade for tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of her Precepts, and will tell thee what thou ſhouldeſt haue done: thy <hi>conſcience</hi> will preſent vnto thy view, the things which thou haſt done, and ſhall pronounce the ſentence of condemnation with ſo ſhrill a voice, that thy deafeſt eare may heare it: this booke of <hi>conſcience</hi> is in thine owne keeping, lockt vp within the cloſet of thine owne boſome; none can falſifie it, neither is there any thing written in this booke, but what thine owne hand hath ſubſcribed therunto; therfore thou canſt not take any exception againſt it. As was Gods proceeding againſt Iuda and Ieruſalem, ſuch ſhall his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding bee againſt the wicked at the day of Iudgement: before he pronounced their Iudgement, hee appealed vnto their owne conſciences, whether they had not deſerued, that God ſhould vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly reiect and forſake them; <hi>O Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of Ieruſalem, and men of Iudah, iudge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 5.</note> 
               <hi>I pray you, betwixt mee and my
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19157:44"/>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard.</hi> Iudge you, that is, looke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your owne conſciences, and there reade your owne ſinnes, and iudge whether you haue not deſerued, that <hi>I ſhould take away the hedge:</hi> that is, leaue off to defend you from your enemies; and ſuffer the Babylonians to inuade and ſpoile you. <hi>Make you deſolate,</hi> that is; deſtitute of politicall gouernment, and <hi>that Briers and Thornes ſhould grow vp:</hi> that is, many of you carried away vnto the Idolatrie, and other ſins of the Babylonians; <hi>and that the clouds ſhould raine no raine:</hi> that is, that you ſhould be depriued of all kind of comforts in your captiuitie, altogether pining with ſorrow,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 137</note> 
               <hi>ſitting downe by the waters of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon weeping, and hanging vp your Harps</hi> vpon the Willow trees that are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. So ſhall it bee at the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, God will appeale vnto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of the wicked, and the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the wicked ſhal frame that deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate concluſion of euerlaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation againſt themſelues. They ſhall not bee brought to the fight of their ſinnes by parables, as Iuda and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19157:45"/>
Ieruſalem here, or as <hi>Dauid,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. But their ſinnes ſhall be written in the book of their conſcience, in ſuch great capitall Letters, that he that runnes may reade it, and ſo ſhall they be eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently conuicted and conuinced by the contents of this booke, and teſtimony of their owne conſcience: ſo that, as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſaid falſely of <hi>Iob,</hi> thine owne mouth, and not I, condemne thee, ſhall the iuſt Iudge of all things at that day ſpeake truly vnto thee by the mouth of thine owne <hi>conſcience,</hi> O thou euill ſeruant, thine owne conſcience bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring witneſſe againſt thee, will I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thee:<note place="margin">Aſcendat itaque ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo tribunal mentis ſuae, ſi timet, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud memi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerit, quod oportet eum ante tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Chriſti exhiberi, Auguſt. Hom. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quicquid enim erubeſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus confiteri, hoe totum proprijs linguis coram totomundo proclam abimus. Et a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertis conſcientiarum libris ſingulis mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtabimus:</hi> Whatſoeuer, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> we now bluſh to confeſſe before men, wee ſhall then proclaime with our own tongues before the whole world, and the booke of our conſcience being laid open, wee ſhall make it manifeſt vnto all men.</p>
            <p>The laſt ſort of accuſers are the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19157:45"/>
creatures without them; the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I ſay, whoſe vſe, by right of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, belong properly vnto none, ſaue vnto the children, of God, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. Howſoeuer, churliſh <hi>Nabals</hi> and couetous <hi>Ahabs,</hi> by vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation doe withhold them from them, the ſinne that is committed in the vſe of them, ſhall riſe vp in iudgement to the condemnation of the wicked. And not onely the ſenſible creatures, groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and trauelling in paine, till they be deliuered from the bondage of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, which againſt their will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnder the wicked: but euen the very ſenſeleſſe creatures, <hi>The heauen ſhall reueale their iniquity, and the earth ſhall riſe vp againſt them, Iob</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 27. The ſtones crying out of the wall, and the beame out of the timber, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 11. that is, they that haue erected their houſes by iniquity, by oppreſſion, by keeping backe the hirelings wages: this their ſinne in ſo doing, ſhall wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt them, nay, the Moth of the garment, and the ruſt of their can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kered coyne, ſhall witneſſe againſt the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19157:46"/>
couetous worldling at the laſt day, <hi>Iames</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 3. Nay, the dead Letter of the Bible, which thou carrieſt about thee, ſhall witneſſe againſt thee, if thou make not good vſe of it. Thus Chriſt told the Iewes, <hi>Doe not thinke that I will accuſe you to my Father: there is one that accuſeth you, euen Moſes in whom yee truſt, Iohn</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 45. <hi>In illa die vltionis nihil habe bit, quod reſpondere poſſit homo pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator, vbi coelum &amp; terra, ſol &amp; Luna, &amp; totus mundus ſtabunt aduerſus nos in Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonium peccatorum noſtrorum, Hugo. de</hi> S. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictor.</hi> In that day what ſhall ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man anſwer for himſelfe, when the Heauen and the Earth, the Sunne, the Moone, the Starres; nay, the whole world wil ſtand vp againſt the wicked, in teſtimony of their ſinnes? and yet if all theſe ſhould hold their peace, <hi>Ipſe cogitationes noſtrae, &amp; ipſa ſpecialiter opera, ſtabunt tante oculos noſtros, nos ante Deum accuſantes, Chryſ. ſuper il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud, Mat.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp; virtutes, &amp;c.</hi> Our very owne thoughts, &amp; eſpecially our owne workes, ſhal ſtand before our eyes, and accuſe vs before God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:19157:46"/>The fift reaſon,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>5</label> why the ſtate and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition of the wicked is ſo full of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror at the day of Iudgement, is, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that fearefull ſentence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, pronounced againſt them by that iuſt and moſt vpright Iudge. Their ſentence is already reuealed vnto them by our Sauiour Chriſt, in the 25. of <hi>S. Matth. verſ.</hi> 41. <hi>Depart from me, yee curſed, into euerlaſting fire, prepared for the Deuill and his Angels.</hi> This ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is very fearefull, whether we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the words themſelues, the Iudge, from whoſe mouth they doe proceede, or the irreuocableneſſe of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Depart from me,</hi>] Thoſe are words of ſeparation; <hi>you curſed,</hi> wordes of deteſtation; <hi>into euerlaſting fire,</hi> words of deſperation; <hi>prepared for the Deuill and his Angels,</hi> a dolefull exemplifiea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Depart from mee:</hi> what ſhall the Creature do, when he is baniſhed from the preſence of the Creator: Oh, the bitter fruit of ſin, which cauſeth the Lord to denie that Creature to be his, as not belonging vnto him, but vtterly to diſclaime him, which once he made
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19157:47"/>
to his owne Image. O, conſider, this in time, who ſhall receiue thee; when God caſts thee out from his face: Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thy ſelfe, euery Creature ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe her comfort to thee, if a drop of cold water might be a reliefe vnto thee, thou ſhalt not get it. But as thy whole life was but a turning backe from the Lord, a wandring, and a going a who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after lying vanities; at that day thou ſhalt receaue this for a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of thine erring, <hi>Depart from me:</hi> and who are they that muſt depart, <hi>the curſed:</hi> they that in their life time haue beene renowned by great and glorious Titles, as King Prince, Duke, Noble, Reuerend, Worſhipfull; now all their glory ſhall bee turned into ſhame, their honor into ignominy, and their ſeemingly bleſſed eſtate, ſhall be turned into a truely curſed: <hi>yee curſed depart from me</hi>; and whither? into fire: and what fire? euerlaſting fire: If this fire were but like that fained fire of Popiſh Purgatory, where venial ſinnes are clenſed, &amp; purged, there were ſome hope that their torments ſhould haue
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19157:47"/>
an end: but they that are caſt into this fire, ſhall there lye, and cry, and fry for euer: <hi>Vbi per millia millia annorum cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciandi, nec tamen in ſecula liberandi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.46.</note> there they ſhall continue a thouſand; nay, ten thouſand; nay, a thouſand thouſand, as many yeares as there are haires vpon thine head, ſtarres in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, drops of water in the Sea, Moates in the Sunne, leaues in Autumne, all theſe muſt be doubled, nay redoubled, euery one muſt be a thouſand, nay ten thouſand, and yet thy torments ſhall not haue an end, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.13.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe, <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> ſetting forth the deſperate eſtate of thoſe that are adiudged to that place, ſaith: <hi>In in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferno nulta eſt redemptio, quoniam qui il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic damnatus, &amp; demerſus fuerit, vlterius non exibit:</hi> In hell there is no redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe he that is adiudged to that place, ſhall neuer come out any more. <hi>In inferno nulla eſt redemptio, quoniam ibi nec pater poteſt adiuuare filium, nec filius patrem</hi>: In hell there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, becauſe there the Father cannot helpe the ſonne, nor the ſonne
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19157:48"/>
the father. <hi>Ibi non inuenitur amicus, aut propinquus, qui valeat argentum, &amp; diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias dare</hi>: There is no friend or neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be found, that will giue a ſum of money, for the ranſome of our ſoule: <hi>None by any meanes can redeeme his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or giue to God a ranſome for him, Pſal.</hi> 49.7. Then ſhall they weepe and howſe bitterly, &amp; by reaſon of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of their paines, ſhal break forth into theſe or the like lamentable excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations: What hath our pride, our ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, our honors, our royall dignities, our riotous kinde of life, all our carnall pleaſures and delights, what haue they profited vs? loe, al things are paſt away, like a dreame, like a ſhaddow, and as a poſte that haſted by, as a ſhip that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ouer the waues of the water, or as a bird flowne through the aire, and are become as if they neuer had been, and hither are we adiudged vnto perpetual paynes, and euerlaſting puniſhments. But neither their weeping, nor their crying,<note place="margin">Auguſt in Ser. ad Erem.</note> nor their ſcreeching, wil auaile them any thing. <hi>In inferno nulla eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptio, quoniam ibi gemitus, ſunt &amp;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19157:48"/>
ſuspiria, &amp; non est qui miſereatur:</hi> In hell there is no redemption, becauſe there is weeping, ſobbing, and ſighing, and yet there is none to take pitty. <hi>Ibi eſt dolor, &amp; planctus, &amp; clamor, &amp; non eſt qui exaudiet:</hi> In hell there is ſorrow, mourning, crying, and yet none that will heare. Then ſhall the wicked wiſh that they had neuer been borne, or that God in their firſt creation had made them ſome creatures of another kinde, as Todes, Serpents, or Cockatrices, for then their miſeries and ſhame ſhould haue ended with their liues. Then ſhall the rent-racking La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dlord wiſh, that he had neuer oppreſſed his poore Tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Then ſhall the couetous Patron wiſh, that hee had neuer made a prey of the Leuites portion. Then ſhall the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Paſtor wiſh, that he had neuer left his flock vnto the hyrelings, who in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Preaching the word of God in ſeaſon, and cut of ſeaſon,</hi> doe tye their flock vnto a ſlender dyet, either a few cold dead <hi>Homilies,</hi> or ſome certayne monethly Sermons, &amp; yet thinke their charge is very ſufficiently diſcharged.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19157:49"/>
Then ſhall the couetous Lawyer wiſh, that hee had neuer ſold his tongue for bribes, to pleade againſt the fatherleſſe and widdowes. Then ſhall the gour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandizing Epicure wiſh, that hee had neuer ſurfetted at his table, and ſuffer the poore to ſtarue at his gate. Then ſhall the carnall Proteſtant wiſh, that he had neuer prattled ſo much of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and practiſed ſo little. Then ſhall the drunkard wiſh, that hee had neuer turned ſo much liquor ouer his tongue, wantonly, &amp; waſtfully, and now want a drop of cold water for to coole his tongue. Then ſhall the wanton forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator wiſh, that hee had neuer waſted his body, and his goods, vpon the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of a ſtrange woman, and withall ſhall confeſſe, that <hi>breuis eſt volupt as fornicationis, ſed perpetua eſt poena for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatoris:</hi> ſhort is the pleaſure of forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but perpetuall is the payne of the fornicator. O conſider this, in time, all ye that forget God! I will conclude with <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> meditation: <hi>Vtinam homines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hom. <hi>13.</hi> in Epiſt. ad Rom.</note> 
               <hi>in tabernis vinarijs, reliquiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> commeſſationibus, &amp; balneis, imo vbique
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19157:49"/>
de gehenna diſputarent:</hi> I would to God that men, euen in wine Tauernes, Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, in their ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quets, in their baths; I will adde, in bawdy houſes, yea euery where would diſpute of Hell. <hi>Non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ſinet in Gehennam incidere, Gehennae meminiſſe:</hi> Men would not run ſo head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to hell, did they but remember hell, did they but meditate on that fire: our common kinde of fire, is but pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fire, in reſpect of that; and yet how hardly can we endure our finger neere it an houre? how much leſſe ſhall wee be able, to dwell eternally in that euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly burning Lake, of fire and brimſtone?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With the Deuil and his Angels.</hi>] The wicked haue ſerued the Deuill, all the dayes of their life, and therefore now they muſt haue an irkſome habitation with the Deuils, and portion of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with his Angels; as it is ſaid, <hi>that the beaſt and the falſe Prophet were cast into the place of eternall torments, with the Deuil, Reuel.</hi> 20.10. And indeede this concluſion of the wicked doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree well with their conuerſation: as
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19157:50"/>
they haue forſaken God, and followed Satan, in obeying his ſinnefull ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, now therefore they ſhall goe their way with Satan, as companions in ſinne, ſo partakers in ſuffering. The body ſhall bee tormented, becauſe it would not obey the ſoule: the ſoule, becauſe it would follow the rebellious body, both ſoule and body, becauſe they obeyed the inſtigation of Satan, and left the directions of Gods holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this Iudge is ſo vpright in iudgement, that in giuing of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt the wicked: firſt, hee cannot erre through ignorance, for he <hi>ſearcheth the heart, and tryeth the reines, to giue vnto euery man according to his wayes, and according to the fruit of his workes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>Ierem.</hi> 17.10. Yea, <hi>all things are naked and open to his eyes,</hi> before whom we muſt appeare. Hee that knew <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt</hi> in the wombe, and ſaw <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanael</hi> vnder the Fig-tree, doth alſo know, and ſee our goings out, and our commings in; he diſcernes <hi>Eſau</hi> from <hi>Iacob</hi>; and knowes faire <hi>Rahel,</hi> from
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19157:50"/>
bleare-eyed <hi>Leah:</hi> hee knowes the thoughts, and intents of our hearts, the words of our mouthes, and the workes of our hands, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.1.2.3.4. and is able to ſet before vs euen our moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he cannot be ouer-ſwayed with fauour, or friendſhip. Indeede in earthly Courts, amongſt the ſonnes of men, <hi>wickedneſſe may bee in the place of Iudgement, Eccleſ.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 16. but in this great Court of heauen, the Iudge will not be parciall to any; <hi>God hath no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, Rom.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 21. but euery one that feareth God, <hi>and worketh righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, ſhall bee accepted at that day.</hi> Nothing will then preuaile, but a pure heart, and an vpright ſpirit: and as for the Iudge, <hi>with righteouſneſſe will hee iudge the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cauſa, non perſona iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicabitur, Martyr.</note> 
               <hi>and the people with equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Pſal.</hi> 58.9. If great men bee found in great ſinnes, they ſhall be adiudged vnto great torments. <hi>Tophet</hi> is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the King, and the pooreſt beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhall then haue as good audience in this Court of Iuſtice, as the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt Monarch in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:19157:51"/>Thirdly, this Iudge cannot be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with power. Indeede amongſt the ſonnes of men, might oftentimes ouer-comes the right; but vnto this Iudge, <hi>all power is giuen both in heauen and earth, Matth.</hi> 28.18. He it was that threw the Angels out of heauen; <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradiſe; <hi>Saul</hi> out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> out of mens ſociety, to conuerſe with beaſts: and he it is that wil humble the high lookes <hi>of man, and abaſe the loftineſſe of men</hi> in that day, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <p>As this Iudge cannot be ouer-ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with power, ſo can he not be bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with pity and compaſſion. The time was indeede when our Sauiour wept ouer Ieruſalem, and made a Sermon full of teares, <hi>O Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, Luke</hi> 19.41. But now, alas, there is no place for pardon, though Ieruſalem ſhould ſeek it with teares. Could thine eyes then ſhead as many teares as there are drops of water in the Sea, yet thou couldeſt not bee able to moue Chriſt vnto compaſſion. The day before the trumpet ſound, mercy ſhal be preached
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19157:51"/>
to the penitent, and beleeuers, by the Goſpell; but from the time that the ſentence is once giuen, there ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be more offring of mercy; the dore ſhall be cloſed: though the wicked cry for mercy, &amp; with <hi>Eſau</hi> ſeeke the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with many teares, yet ſhall they neuer finde it. But as Chriſt doth now <hi>weepe</hi> for the ſinners conuerſion, ſo wil hee then <hi>laugh</hi> at the ſinners deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, this Iudge cannot be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with bribes, which amongſt the ſonnes of men peruert iuſtice, &amp; blinde the eyes of thoſe that ſit in Iudgement: for the richeſt in the world muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare naked and empty-ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, before Chriſt, as naked as euer wee came into the world, and nakeder then euer we went out of the world, by as much as a winding ſheet comes vnto: <hi>Riches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>gold and ſiluer, auaileth not in the day of wrath, but righteouſnes ſaueth the ſoule.</hi> I will conclude with <hi>Auguſtine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. de Symb. l. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iudex ille nec gratiâ praeuenietur, nec miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiâ flectetur, nec fletibus mitigabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:19157:52"/>This Iudge will not be preuented with fauour, moued with mercy nor mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with teares, <hi>nec ſententia eius lata vnquam reuocabitur</hi>; neither will the ſentence once paſt againſt them, euer bee reuoked any more; which is the third thing that I am to ſpeake of.</p>
            <p>This ſentence is the more dreadfull, becauſe it is irreuocable: ſentence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the Iudgement ſeate of mortall men, may be reuoked, or ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by ſundry meanes: as firſt, by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing vnto ſome higher Iudge; as <hi>Paul</hi> appealed vnto <hi>Caeſar:</hi> but at this great Aſſiſe there is no higher Iudge, for <hi>he is the onely and bleſſed Prince, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.15. <hi>And the Father hath committed all Iudgement vnto him, Ioh.</hi> 5.27.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Iudge vpon better and more mature deliberation, may alter his opinion: but there is no alteration of Iudgement, when it is once gone forth from the Throne of the Lord, whoſe Iudgements are more reſolute, then the Decrees of the Medes and Perſians, which might not bee altered. When
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19157:52"/>
               <hi>Eſau</hi> came to his father for a bleſſing, which was formerly paſt to <hi>Iacob,</hi> his father ſaid, <hi>I haue bleſſed him, and hee ſhall be bleſſed, Gen.</hi> 27.33. So reſolute ſhall the Lords ſentence be at the day of Iudgement: I haue curſed them, and they ſhall bee curſed: and as <hi>Balaam</hi> ſaid vnto <hi>Balak, The Lord hath bleſſed, and he cannot reuerſe it, Numb.</hi> 23.20. So ſay I, The Lord will not reuerſe this his ſentence of malediction, <hi>Goe ye curſed</hi>: neither will hee alter the thing <hi>that is gone out of his lippes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. By ſupplication: but, becauſe the wicked turned away their cares from hearing the Lord, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them by his Word, it ſhall bee iuſt with God not to lend an eare, when they doe call and cry vnto him: there is not any of that glorious Court of Heauen, that will friend them ſo much as to ſpeake a word in their behalfe. Should the Saints, whom they euer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, <hi>accounting their life madneſſe, and their end to be without honour? Wiſ.</hi> 5.4. Should the Angels, whoſe Miniſtry they haue refuſed and abuſed? if they
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19157:53"/>
did, ſhould God himſelfe heare them, whoſe Spirit they haue ſo oftentimes grieued? And therefore <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid well, There is no vmpire, when God and man are at oddes, <hi>Iob</hi> 9.33.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ </seg>6</label> Now the laſt Reaſon which doth aggrauate the horrour of the wicked, <hi>is the puniſhment of loſſe</hi>;<note place="margin">Schol. poena damni.</note> the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Heauens baniſhment, and Hels eternall impriſonment, is a ſufficient torture vnto the ſoule of the wicked, and as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> iudgeth it to bee much more bitter and irkſome, then the paines of Hell;<note place="margin">Duplex eſt damnato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum poena: nam &amp; mentem vrit triſtitia &amp; corpus flamma, Iſidorus de meditatione Ignis gehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis.</note> yea, worſe then a thouſand Hells if there were ſo many, <hi>Chryſoſt. ſuper Mat. Hom.</hi> 33. accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Sauiours ſaying, <hi>There ſhall be weeping, and gnaſhing of teeth, when they ſhall ſee Abraham, Iſaac and Iacob, and all the Prophets in the Kingdome of God, and they themſelues thruſt out of dore, Luk.</hi> 13.18. <hi>VVhere ſhal be Dogges, and Enchanters, and VVhoremongers, and Murtherers, and Idolaters, and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer loueth or maketh lies, Reuel.</hi> 22.15. And not only ſhall they be debard of the ioyes of Heauen, and glory of the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19157:53"/>
Saints, but they ſhall be depriued of all Earthly comforts, and all their former delights. <hi>The Pome granat tree, the Palm tree, the Apple tree ſhall wither; the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples after which their ſoule luſted, ſhall depart from them, and they ſhall finde none</hi>: Yea, if a drop of cold water would comfort them, it ſhall be denied them; The Epicure ſhall bee depriued of his daintie diſhes, the Drunkard, of his bowles of wine, the Adulterer, of his wanton Miſtris, the Couetous, and Vſurer, of their gold, which they made their God. To conclude, they ſhall be depriued of all Heauenly ioyes, of all earthly comforts.</p>
            <p>But I will begin to ſing a Song of melody, and proclaime a yeere of Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le vnto the children of God: <hi>Conſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, conſolemini; Lift vp your heads</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt) <hi>for your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption draweth neere, Luke</hi> 21.28. There is a great Emphaſis in the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which doth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a freedome from captiuity, &amp; a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring vnto a former libertie. As if our Sauiour ſhould ſay, The Church, as lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19157:54"/>
as ſhe is in this world, ſhe is like Iſrael vnder <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> held captiue in impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment and ſlauerie: But now at this great Aſſiſe, there ſhall be a gaole-deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, an euerlaſting freedome from all euils whatſoeuer: our life is wouen full of miſeries;<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>90.10.</hi> Diu viuere eſt diu tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queri, Aug. Tertul. vita carcer.</note> the beſt of it is but labour and griefe. We are borne into the world weeping and bewailing, as it were, our owne enſuing miſeries; the progreſſe of our life is labor, the end is griefe. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was neuer wearier of the dungeon, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> of the Den of Lions, <hi>Dauid</hi> to dwel in the Tents of Kedar, then the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God are to remaine ſo long in the Land of Egypt, in the Priſon of this world; and therefore it is ſaid, that they looke and long <hi>for a Citie to come, whoſe Builder and Maker is God.</hi> But then ſhall we be euerlaſtingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from all the miſeries and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, which now we are ſubiect vnto: the ſoule ſhall be deliuered from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordred paſſions, as hope, feare, ioy and ſorrow: the body from ſundry out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward calamities, as ſickneſſe, paine, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, reproch, from prouocations and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19157:54"/>
intiſements of the wicked world, from the power of the deuil, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſlauery of ſin, from death, from hell; it is our mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage day, when our rotten bones ſhall be raiſed out of the duſt of the earth: &amp; we ſhalbe clad with glory, &amp; ſhal meet Chriſt in the clouds,<note place="margin">1. <hi>The.</hi> 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſhal be euer with the Lord</hi>: Where we ſhall haue an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Sabbath, ioy vpon euery ones head: ſorrow &amp; ſighing ſhal flee away. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal <hi>we ſee God face to face,</hi> &amp; that <hi>with theſe eyes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob. God ſhall wipe away all teares from our eyes, there ſhall be nö more death, neither ſorrow, nor cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, neither ſhal there be any more paine, Reuel.</hi> 21.4. There ſhall be no more Winter, nor Summer, heat nor cold, day nor night, death nor hel. But there ſhall be <hi>Vita ſine morte, Dies ſine nocte, ſecuritas ſine timore, &amp;c.</hi> There ſhall be life without death, day without night, ſecurity without feare, pleaſure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paine, tranquillity without labour, beauty without deformity, ſtrength without weakneſſe, euery thing that is good, without any thing that is bad: To conclude, <hi>Eye hath not ſeene, nor
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19157:55"/>
eare heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that loue him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.4.</note> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. Let the faithfull ſoule ſigh out this meditation, with bleſſed <hi>Gregory, Bone Ieſu, verbum patris, doce me facere volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem tuam, vt à ſpiritu tuo bono ductus, ad beatam illam proueniam ciuitatem.</hi> O ſweet Ieſus, thou that art the word of the Father, teach me thy wil, that being guided by thy good Spirit, I may bee brought vnto that Citty, where there is <hi>Certa ſecuritas, ſecura aeternitas, &amp; ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna tranquillitas, &amp; tranquilla foelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, &amp; foelix ſuauitas, &amp; ſuauis iucu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditas.</hi> Where there is Security, Eternity, Tranquillity, Felicity. <hi>Vbi tu Deus cum Patre &amp; Spiritu Sancto, regnas per in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finita ſecula.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. in Pſal. ſept.</note> Where thou doſt raigne as God, with the holy Ghoſt, world without end. Let vs therefore ſtand with our loynes girded, like good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants waiting for their maſter: Let vs pray, that this Kingdome would come; &amp; let vs ingeminate that of the Spouſe, the Church of Chriſt, <hi>Come, Lord Ieſu, come quickly, Apoc.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:19157:55"/>And here let vs reſt our thoughts a while, and ſettle our meditations on ſerious conſideration of this great day, not curiouſly to define or determine, how farre, or how neere, the day or yeere when theſe things ſhall be, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lockt from vs, and kept vnreuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the ſecret counſell of God: yet wading herein as farre as <hi>Hercules</hi> Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, that is, as farre as the <hi>word of God</hi> will conduct: but where the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> is ſilent, and hath not a tongue to ſpeake, my penne ſhall not indite, nor my eare liſten thereunto. And firſt I will ſet downe the opinions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectures of others, touching the end of the world. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reckoneth vp ſix Ages of the world,<note place="margin">Auguſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> in Gen. con. Manichaeos.</note> the firſt from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> to <hi>Noah,</hi> the ſecond, from <hi>Noah</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> the third from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Dauid,</hi> the fourth from <hi>Dauid,</hi> to the captiuity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the fift fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the captiuity of <hi>Babylon</hi> vnto Chriſt, the ſixt from Chriſt, vnto the end of all things, the day of Iudgement. So that this Age in which we liue, is the laſt Age, and may bee termed the decrepit
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19157:56"/>
and old-age of the world: and if Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> time was the laſt howre, then ſurely theſe our times are the laſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes: <hi>Then now the end of all things is at hand, and wee are they vpon whom the ends of the world are come,</hi> and Chriſt is ready to iudge the quick and the dead. But how long this laſt Age, being the dotage of the world, will continue, it is conceald from men and Angels. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> told his friend <hi>Heſchius</hi> (curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly inquiring of the end of the world) that hee durſt not meaſure, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit or determine the times and ſeaſons which God hath put in his owne pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; it may be euery mans anſwere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all ſuch curious queſtioniſts. There are very many of the learned Rabbins,<note place="margin">Oraculum a ſchola Eliae.</note> who being ledde by their owne vaine and weake coniectures, would ſeeme to ſet downe a certaine ſet time of the end of the world, poſitiuely affirming the world ſhall indure ſix thouſand yeeres, and thoſe yeeres they doe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute into two thouſand before the Law, two thouſand vnder the Law, two thouſand after the Law; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:19157:56"/>
ſome other faine, that the world ſhall indure ſix dayes, as it was made in ſix dayes, &amp; the length of euery day to bee a thouſand yeeres; as if it had beene <hi>Dauids</hi> meaning where he ſaith, that <hi>A thouſand yeeres in thy ſight are as yeſterday, Pſal.</hi> 90 <hi>v.</hi> 4. Whereas his meaning is, that all things paſt, and to come, are preſent with God. Indeede it is the Deuils policy, becauſe hee would haue vs to put off farre from vs the euill day, and with the ſluggard in the Prouerbs, deſire yet <hi>a little more ſleepe, a little more ſlumber,</hi> to buſie vs with an infinite many of friuolous, idle, and vnprofitable queſtions, that we may neglect that <hi>one thing which is neceſſary:</hi> as namely, a careful prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, rather then a curious inquiry, to <hi>watch and pray,</hi> according to our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours counſell, leſt that day come on vs vnawares, and we found ſleeping: for as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> truly; Prophecies are ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner fulfilled, then vnderſtood.<note place="margin">Prophetias impleri qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intelligi, Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Of that day and houre knoweth no man, no not the Angels in heauen, neither the Sonne, but the Father, Mark.</hi> 13.32. If our
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19157:57"/>
Sauiour would haue reuealed this day vnto any, doubtleſſe hee would haue reuealed it vnto his Apoſtles, his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries, his fauourites, his followers, vnto whom hee imparted greater things, and better things, yet hee tels them flatly, <hi>Non eſt veſtrum noſſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora, &amp;c. It is not for you to know the times or the ſeaſons, which the Father hath put in his owne power, Act.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Of the day and houre knoweth no man, no not the Angels.</hi> The Angels abound with much knowledge, <hi>naturall, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentall,</hi> and <hi>reuealed,</hi> vnto whom God himſelfe doth reueale certaine Ambaſſages to conuay vnto his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and hauing farre better meanes of knowledge then wee haue, for as much as they know God <hi>intuendo,</hi> by his looking in his face, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.10. But wee haue our knowledge, <hi>diſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo,</hi> by diſcuſſing, reaſoning, diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and that not a <hi>priori</hi> neither, but a <hi>poſteriori,</hi> by his backe parts, as hee hath manifeſted himſelfe in his works, being <hi>mirabilis in maximis, mirabilis in minimis,</hi> wonderfull in all his workes:
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19157:57"/>
               <hi>The inuiſible things of him are clearely ſeen in the creation of the world, and are vnderſtood by the things that are made, Rom.</hi> 1.20. And yet <hi>of that day and houre knoweth no man, no, not the Angels in heauen, neither the Sonne.</hi> To let paſſe <hi>Epiphanius</hi> interpretation,<note place="margin">Epiphanij in illum lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio eſt valdè arguta &amp; detorta, Martyr.</note> &amp; his witty, but wreſted diſtinction of a twofold knowledge, <note n="*" place="margin">Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae.</note> I will, vnder the correction of the Learned, ſhew, how Chriſt knowes the day, &amp; yet how he is ignorant of it. It ſhould ſeeme ſtrange, that the wiſedome of God ſhould bee ignorant of thoſe things which are in God, neither can it be ſaid, that Chriſt being GOD and man, in one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon together;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> his Deity ſhould not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his Humanity, as our ſoule doth the body, but leaue it deſtitute of knowledge: for in Chriſt, ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. <hi>i.</hi> in his humane nature, <hi>dwelleth the fulneſſe of the Godhead bodily, Coloſ.</hi> 2.9. Chriſt himſelfe being the beſt and trueſt interpretour of his owne words, thus expounds himſelfe, <hi>As the Father gaue me commandement, euen ſo I doe, Iohn</hi> 14.31. Therefore becauſe Chriſt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19157:58"/>
was ſent as an Ambaſſadour, to declare and manifeſt the will of the Father, hee would neither do, or ſpeake any thing, but that vnto the which end hee was ſent: as therefore hee was an Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, ſent out of the boſome of the Father, he is ſaid to be ignorant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had no commiſſion to reueale it:<note place="margin">Aquinas part. <hi>3.</hi> q. <hi>10.</hi> Art. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> According to that of <hi>Aquinas, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur neſcire, quia non facit ſcire</hi>: He is ſaid not to know, becauſe hee would not haue vs to know; thus hee told his Diſciples, <hi>It is not for you to know the times and the ſeaſons, Act.</hi> 1.7. I will conclude with the ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine, Ne nos addamus inquirere, quòd ille non addidit dicere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>146.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Secret things belong vnto the Lord, reuealed things vnto vs, Deu.</hi> 29. <hi>verſe</hi> 29. Let vs not dare to pry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Arke of the Lord, ſtriuing to know that which is impoſſible for vs to know, it being reſerued vnreuealed within the ſecret boſome of his ſacred Maieſty.</p>
            <p>The word of God affoordeth vs cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſignes and prognoſticks, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee may conclude of a certainty,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19157:58"/>
that that day is not farre off: the firſt is this:</p>
            <p>The reuealing and comming of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt. <hi>Antichriſt muſt firſt come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Antichriſt the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of the end of the world.</note> ſo ſaith the Apoſtle. <hi>That Man of ſin muſt firſt bee reuealed, before that day come, that ſonne of perdition,</hi> 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>Little children,</hi> ſaith S. Iohn, <hi>it is the laſt time: and as you haue heard Antichrist ſhall come, euen now are there many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts, whereby we may know that it is the laſt time,</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.18. I neede not proue that the Pope of Rome is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: many by their writings haue made this plaine and apparent, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered that Man of ſinne, vnto the whole world, as manifeſt to bee Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, as he is Pope.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſigne, that the day is at hand, <hi>is,</hi> an Apoſtaſie from Faith, and from ſound Doctrine, of which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh: <hi>Now the Spirit ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth expreſly, that in the latter times, ſome ſhall depart from the faith, giuing heed to ſeducing ſpirits, and doctrines of Deuils,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. And is not this time come to paſſe already? are not many
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19157:59"/>
carryed about like vapours in the ayre, with euery blaſt of vaine Doctrine, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing itching eares, affecting alwayes ſome new fangled point or other? what a diſpute beginnes there to bee about that Twinne of our ſaluation, <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> touching the priority of them? which makes me thinke, that either men haue no repentance, or elſe no faith: vnleſſe both conſiſt vpon the tippe of the tongue, in prattling, not in practice.</p>
            <p>The third is the promulgation of the Goſpell <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, throughout the whole world. So ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, And this <hi>Goſpell of the Kingdom ſhall bee preached throughout the whole world, and then ſhall the end come,</hi> Mat. 24.14. <hi>It muſt bee publiſhed among all Nations, Mar.</hi> 13.10. And is not the ſound thereof already gone forth into the ends of the earth? is it not ſpred al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready from <hi>Dan,</hi> euen vnto <hi>Beerſheba?</hi> from one Sea coaſt vnto another?</p>
            <p>The fourth is, the riſing vp of falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets. <hi>Many ſhall come in my name</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19157:59"/>
Chriſt) <hi>ſaying, I am Chriſt, and the time draweth neere,</hi> Luke 21.8. <hi>And many falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue many,</hi> Matth. 24.11.</p>
            <p>The fift ſigne is, <hi>Iniquity ſhal abound,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The fift ſigne is the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of ſinne.</note> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.12. There ſhall bee ſuch a generall infection of ſinne, <hi>Men ſhall be louers of their owne ſelues, couetous, boſters, proude, blaſphemers, diſobedient to parents, vnthankefull, vnholy, without naturall affection, truce-breakers, falſe accuſers, incontinent, fierce, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good; Traytors, heady, high minded, louers of pleaſures, more then lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of God, hauing a forme of godlines, but deny the power thereof,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.2.3.4. And this is Gods ordinary procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againſt ſinne, hee doth neuer pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh generall, vntill ſinne bee growne generall. God neuer waſht away the inhabitants of the earth, with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of his wrath, <hi>vntill all fleſh had cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted his way vpon the earth, vntill the earth was filled with cruelty, and all the imaginations of the thoughts of mans heart were euill, onely euill, continually euill, Gen.</hi> 6.5.11.12. The Lord neuer
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19157:60"/>
rayned downe fire and brimſtone from the Lord, out of heauen, vpon thoſe two Cities, <hi>Simeon and Leui</hi> like, ſiſters in ſinne, vntill hee had made enquiry whether there were any righteous men amongſt them; for the Lord, had it not derogated from his Iuſtice, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently from his glory, in not being a iuſt reuenger of ſinne, was as willing, and as well contented, as <hi>Abraham,</hi> that Sodom ſhould be ſaued, for euery petition returned vnto <hi>Abraham</hi> with ſome aduantage: and moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is it, the Lord neuer ceaſed graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, till <hi>Abraham</hi> ceaſed asking; but in the end there being ſuch a penury, ſuch a ſcarcity, ſuch a nullity of good men, that the Lord deſtroyed them with fire and brimſtone, and ſo it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines vntill this day, as a monument of Gods wrath,<note place="margin">Mare mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum.</note> a Sea of fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone. If we trauell vnto that great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ieruſalem, the Metropolis of the world, the Lady of the earth, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of beauty, wee ſhall finde it but a heape of ſtones. But what did moue the Lord to deſtroy ſo famous a City,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19157:60"/>
called the City of God, the habitation of the moſt Higheſt, a place where he did delight to dwell? yet ſin had made her infamous and odious in the ſight of God: the contagion and infection of ſinne was generall, and that not only ſome kinde of ſinnes, but all ſinne, <hi>all oppreſſion,</hi> that is, all kinde of ſinne:<note place="margin">Synechdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſpeciei.</note> and well may it bee, for oppreſſion is a cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinne, and they that make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of great ſinnes, ſurely, will not make conſcience of leſſer; and theſe ſinnes were not committed in corners, or by-lanes, but in the open ſtreets, in the market place; men were growne impudent in ſinne; <hi>all oppreſſion was in the midſt of Ieruſalem, Ierem.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. ſinne was growne generall, <hi>Ieruſalem was a denne of Theeues</hi>; there was no righteous man found throughout the whole City, that executed iudgement, and ſought the truth; No, nor at the Court, amongſt the great Men, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the Rulers, amongſt the Noblemen, <hi>Theſe haue altogether broken the yoke, and burſt the bond</hi>: no, nor yet amongſt the Prophets, for they propheſie falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:19157:61"/>
and the Prieſts beare rule by their meanes, that is, both agree together, in a mutuall and meere colluſion of the people, as the Pope with his orders of begging Fryers: firſt, they robbe and deceiue the people, and then they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the ſpoile, <hi>Ierem.</hi> 5.1.5.31. To conclude, ſinne was as generall in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, as euer it was in the old world when it was deſtroyed with water, or in Sodome, that City of pride, luxury, idleneſſe, when it was burnt with fire; ſo Ieruſalems puniſhments were para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell to her ſinnes; her ſinnes were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, her iudgements were as gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: There is not one ſtone left vpon another, of ſo many ſtately buildings, on which the Iewes ſo confidently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed,<note place="margin">Ioſeph. l. <hi>6.</hi> hiſt. Iud.</note> and ſo preſumptuouſly inſulted ouer the Romanes, ſaying, that if the Romans had wings, yet they could not flye ouer their wals, and inuade their City.</p>
            <p>And is not ſinne growne as generall in this world, as euer 'twas in the old world, or in Sodome, or in Ieruſalem? may we not as iuſtly take vp the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19157:61"/>
of <hi>Iſay</hi> in his time? <hi>Both head is ſicke, and heart is heauie, Iſai</hi> 1.5. where, by <hi>head</hi> (as Interpreters obſerue) is meant the King (for the Prophet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vnto the Iewes, as if they were one body) and when the Prophet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of this ſickneſſe of the head, he meant <hi>Ahaz,</hi> who then was head of the Kingdome, and his diſeaſe was not in the foote, as <hi>Aſa</hi> his gout, but in the corruption of his life, <hi>hee did nothing that was right in the ſight of the Lord his God,</hi> 2. <hi>K.</hi> 16.2. &amp; the hart is the Prieſts that if they be ſuch as they ſhould be, may very well reſemble the heart, that as the heart communicateth vitall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits vnto the whole body, ſo the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God ſhould endeuour to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the life of grace in euery mans ſoule: But if, like the heart, they do not employ themſelues in their peculiar of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and dutie, preaching the Word of God in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the members that are dead in ſin, and endeuouring daily the conuerſion of ſoules, by wholſome doctrine, and holy conuerſation; then are they not
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19157:62"/>
hearts any longer, but harmes, and in Gods due time they ſhall bee trodden vnder foote like clay in the ſtreete, or caſt out with vnſauory ſalt to the dounghill. The foot may not find fault with head or heart: only I will ingemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the Prophets words, <hi>Both head is ſick, and hart is heauy</hi>: The matter which I haue in hand, forceth mee to ſhew the generalitie of ſinne, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the propinquity of the general Iudgement. If God ſhould look downe from heauen vpon the children of men, and marke what is done amiſſe in this our ſinful Sublunarie, he may ſee that al are gone aſide, euen from the higheſt to the loweſt, from the youngeſt to the eldeſt, from the richeſt to the pooreſt, from the Eagle to the Wren, <hi>They are altogether become abominable, there is none that doth good, no, not one, Pſalme</hi> 14.3. The foundations of the Earth are out of courſe, ſinne hath gotten the vpper hand, iniquity aboundeth, vertue is diſgraced, vice aduanced. Sin now adaies is growne vnto ſuch a preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that notwithſtanding the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:19157:62"/>
ſword of Authoritie, which vnleſſe it lay vnſheathed in the hand of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, <hi>bearìng it in vaine,</hi> were able to deſtroy this Hydra of ſinne, though new heads budded out continually. It it recorded of a French Ambaſſador in the time of King <hi>Richard</hi> the third, how he told the King, that there were three great Whores in England, Pride, Couetouſneſſe, Luxurie: If this Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador were to come againe, he may tell the King, that there are more then tenne times three; not a ſinne but hath his mate: Pride and Ambition, Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe and Extortion, Adultery and Fornication, Flattery and Diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Strife and Contention, Swearing and Forſwearing, Lying and Curſed ſpeaking, Chambering and Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Strife and Enuying; nay, more ſinnes then I can name,<note place="margin">Si ſuperbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entibus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis Deus no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pepercit, quantò mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nùs tibi putredo &amp; vermis? Bernard.</note> and ſuch ſinnes as are not to be named.</p>
            <p>To inſiſt a while vpon ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, to begin firſt with the firſt, that firſt ſinne of Pride, ſo hatefull in the higheſt Eye, that it threw the Angels out of Heauen, whereby they became
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:19157:63"/>
reprobate Deuils: and yet no ſinne ſo common, none growne more generall, then this ſinne of Pride. Were the daughters of Zion euer more proud and haughtie, then our Dames of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land? who are ſo farre from being like <hi>women that profeſſe the feare of God,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.10. that they ſcarce looke like the creatures of God, being ſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create ofttimes, and ſo deformed with their French, their Spaniſh, and their fooliſh faſhions, with their Plumes, Fannes, Feathers and Fardingales, Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet Vizards, that they looke rather like ſome Antickes, Maskers, May games? <hi>Eſaias</hi> Text of faſhions is multiplied by the fancies of our time: <hi>Their bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and their bracelets, their ſlippers and their mufflers, their vailes, their wimples, and their criſping pinnes, their round ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers like the Moone, Iſaiah</hi> 3.19. Yet he makes no mention of the yellow Ruffes, of their perfumed ſhagged haire, which neuer grew vpon their ownehead; nor of their painted faces: a pretty artificiall meanes to mend the workmanſhip of their Maker. But I
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:19157:63"/>
thinke, that the Myſtery of this art may rather be reduced to the common place of whoriſhneſſe, or in a nearer tearme, the <hi>attire of an harlot, Prou.</hi> 7. that as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaid of a Lyar, <hi>Oftende mihi mendacem, &amp; oſtendam tibifurem,</hi> ſhew me a Lyar, and I wil ſhew thee a thiefe: ſo ſhew mee a painted face, may I ſay, and I will ſhew thee a whore, for ſhee dwels at the Signe of a painted face. Neither is this ſinne of pride peculiar vnto women onely, but alſo to men, for they are almoſt become like vnto wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as though they were willing to change ſexes with them. In the time of Popery, as one ſaies wittily, England was made an Aſſe to beare the burthen of the Popes taxations: but now Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is metamorphoſed into an Ape, an imitator of all faſhions, of all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Nations, France, Spaine and Italy, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To leaue pride as an vgly monſter, and to ſpeake of the generalitie of the ſinne of whoredom, which deſerues the ſecond place in Satans Kingdome: The baſe-begotten-baſtard-broode that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19157:64"/>
this ſin brings foorth into the world, manifeſts the generality of it: for almoſt what Pariſh within this Kingdom, nay, almoſt in the whole world, but hath an adulterous iſſue within it? and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as one hath none, another hath two. Beſide, how is the bed of honourable marriage abuſed by vnlawfull mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? God that is <hi>vnus</hi> one, as <hi>Bernard, Vniſſimus,</hi> moſt one, hath made <hi>vnam,</hi> one woman <hi>vni,</hi> for one man, and one man for one woman; ſo ſpeakes the Prophet; <hi>And did hee not make one?</hi> where God ſends vs backe to the cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, and firſt inſtitution of marriage, he made one man for one woman, <hi>Adam</hi> for <hi>Eue,</hi> and ioyned them both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one inuiolable band of honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wedlock, <hi>Ge.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Yet had he abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſpirit,</hi> that is, by that ſelfe ſame ſecret inſpiration, whereby <hi>Adam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a liuing ſoule, by that ſame pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull influence, if I may ſo ſpeake, God could haue created more men for one woman, yet he did not. And why would he not? <hi>Becauſe he ſought a godly ſeede</hi>; that is, as marriage is honourable, ſo
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:19157:64"/>
the fruite of this diuine ordinance ſhould bee holy, not illigitimate, not baſtards, not a promiſcuous ſeede, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lach.</hi> 2.15. But alas, how is the ende of marriage peruerted? how doth <hi>euery man neigh after his neighbours wife? Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie</hi> 5.8. That is, men are as ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and as reſolutely impudent in this filthy fact, like <hi>welfed horſes, that haue no vnderſtanding, Pſalm.</hi> 32.9. which the Prophet calles the ſinne of <hi>abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Ezek.</hi> 22.11. How doth euery man <hi>lay waite at his neighbours doore? Iob</hi> 31.4. that is, by priuate ſtealth, to warme anothers bed, leauing <hi>their own ciſternes, the wife of their youth, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the boſome of the ſtranger, Prou.</hi> 5. But I will leaue this ſinne in ſecret where it is committed: for the ſilent night onely is guiltie of theſe vnchaſt actions, and ſecret chambers are only priuie vnto theſe works of darkeneſſe: this ſin is more ſuſpected then knowne, and yet knowne too well, to be too too generall.</p>
            <p>Drunkenneſſe may be the third head of this monſtrous Hel-hound, and <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berus</hi>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:19157:65"/>
of ſinne: how generall is this ſhameleſſe, ſwiniſh, idle, baſe, beaſtly ſinne growne! It was once but one mans ſinne, and of infirmity too, as not knowing the vertue of the grape,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> nor the qualitie of that liquor: and long ſince it hath beene ſcorned, as the beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers fault. Hence came the Prouerbe, <hi>As drunke as the Begger.</hi> But now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes it is reputed not only the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingmans complement, but the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans grace. <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpake wel of theſe times, <hi>Habebitur aliquando abrietati ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, &amp; plurimum caepiſſe vini, virtus erit,</hi> The time ſhall come, that honour ſhall be attributed to drunkenneſſe, and to drinke much wine, ſhall bee accounted vertue and valour. How many now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies draw their whole Patrimonie thorow their throate; making a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, almoſt a profeſſion of drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>riſing vp earely to follow ſtrong drinke, and ſo continue vntill night, till wine enflame them? Iſaiah</hi> 5.11. And as the Wiſe man ſpeaks, <hi>tarrie long at the wine, Prou.</hi> 23.29. Our Tauernes, our Innes, and Alehouſes, were they well
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:19157:65"/>
lookt into by the Magiſtrate, would yeeld too many of ſuch kind of ſtayers by, who, vnder pretence of drinking a pot or two, fill their braines ere they go away and emptie their purſe.</p>
            <p>I will not inſiſt any longer in diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Satans kingdom. From the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of theſe ſins, we may conclude an vniuerſalitie of all the reſt. What ſin is there, but is growne as generall, as euer the Plague was in any citie or countrie? like <hi>Naamans</hi> leproſie, it hath ouerſpred the whole body; <hi>From the ſole of the foote, to the crowne of the head, there is no ſoundnes, but wounds, ſwellings, &amp; putrifying ſores, Iſa.</hi> 1.6. Sin is growne vnto ſuch an height, and to ſuch a head, that it is ſafer for a man to commit ſin, then to reproue it; <hi>and hee that refrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his foote,</hi> and runneth not into the ſame exceſſe of riot, ſhall <hi>be a prey,</hi> a ſcorne, a by word, a deriſion, a laughing ſtocke. <hi>Behold, the regions are white vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to harueſt,</hi> ſinne is ripe, euen to the full growth; and therefore aſſuredly it will not be long ere the Lord ſends foorth his Labourers, thoſe winged executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of his wrath, with ſickles in their
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:19157:66"/>
hands, to gather the wicked into bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, that they may be caſt into hell. It is the Lords gracious and mercifull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation to prorogue a while the tearme of his comming, becauſe wee ſhould haue a little more time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in, and ſo be left without leſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe. Let vs then vſe the Lords pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as a ſpurre and prouocation vnto repentance, ſo ſaith the bleſſed Apoſtle propheſying of the Atheiſts of our time, who doe not ſticke to ſay, <hi>VVhere is the promiſe of his comming</hi>? Sheweth what vſe they ſhould make of the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſlacknes of his comming, <hi>his long ſuffering,</hi> is an argument that the Lord <hi>is not willing, that any ſhould periſh, but that al ſhould come to repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> 2. <hi>Pe.</hi> 3.9 And thus mercifully the Lord dealt with the old world; after hee had threatned their deſtruction, hee gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>one hundred and twenty yeeres to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in, Gen.</hi> 6.3. Put not then off farre from thee the euill day: if the Lord ſeemes ſlack, it is becauſe thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt flye ſpeedily with <hi>Lot</hi> vnto <hi>Zoar,</hi> that is, accelerate thy repentance. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God hath already whet his
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:19157:66"/>
ſword, and bent his bow, and made it ready, how ſoeuer he may ſeeme ſlack, yet he may eaſily come before thou art ready; if hee doth come, thou being vnprepared and vnprouided, aſſuredly he will pay thee home for thus abuſing his patience. The Heathen writer could ſay thus much,<note place="margin">Valer. Max.</note> 
               <hi>Deum grauitate ſupplicij compenſare tarditatem puniendi,</hi> the greatneſſe of his puniſhment ſhall recompence the ſlackneſſe of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, when he doth come: when <hi>Deus &amp; dies vltionum conuenerint,</hi> when the God of vengeance, and the day of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance ſhall meet together, thou ſhalt bee payed home for altogether. I will conclude with that queſtioned. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour to the Hebrewes: <hi>Yet a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while, and he that ſhall come, wil come, and will not tarry,</hi> Heb. 10.37.</p>
            <p>The laſt vſe ſhall bee an exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to repentance, and that betime, while wee haue time: <hi>Walke,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>in the day, Iohn</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 9. that is, in thy life, which is but a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a ſpanne of time, <hi>The night com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth wherein no man can worke, Iohn</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 4. that is, the night of thy death,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:19157:67"/>
which is the concluſion of the day of thy life, and then there is no more time to worke out our ſaluation. For an Angell hath ſworne from <hi>heauen, by him that liueth for euermore, that time ſhall be no more, Apoc.</hi> 10.6. that is, after this acceptable time, no more time for repentance, no more daies of ſaluation. The Apoſtle wils vs to <hi>doe good while we haue time,</hi> intimating therby, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this time,<note place="margin">Cypr.</note> there is no more time. <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae aut hic amittitur aut tenetur: cùm iſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinc exceſſum fuerit, nullus poenitentiae lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, nullus ſatisfactionis effectus:</hi> Life here is either got or loſt; for when we goe out of the body, there is no place for repentance, no effect of ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; if we haue ſinned to day, and haue not repented, it may be wee ſhall haue leaue of the Lords patience, to learne it better another day: but after the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migration of the ſoule from the body, there remaines nothing elſe, but a <hi>fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full looking for of iudgement.</hi> It ſtands vs therefore vpon the ſaluation of our ſoule, to looke before wee leape, to be certaine that wee haue one foote vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the border of <hi>Canaan,</hi> before wee
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:19157:67"/>
leaue our earthly tabernacle. Let vs make our election ſure vnto vs, by true and ſpeedy repentance; and ſeale vp this comfortable concluſion to our ſoules, that our ſinnes are pardoned in the bloud of Chriſt. Suppoſe that the generall day of Iudgement were farre off, and that this day of ſaluation were to ſhine vpon this Land, ſtill on to the worlds end: yet what is that to thee or mee? the day of grace endeth to thee and mee, at the day of our death; after that, the Lord ſhall neuer offer mercy vnto vs. It is the gracious and merciful diſpenſation of almighty God, who when hee may iuſtly cut thee off, as thou art committing of ſinne, and throwe thee downe to hell, yet hee giues thee ſpace and time to repent of this thy ſinning, and ſo thy ſinnes may bee done away. Thus our Sauiour ſpeaking of <hi>that woman Iezabel:</hi> for ſo the holy Ghoſt points her out, by the finger, as it were in contempt, ſaith, <hi>That hee gaue her ſpace to repent of her fornication, and ſhee repented not, Reuel.</hi> 2.21. Meaning, hee did let her liue to repent, whereas if hee had cut
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:19157:68"/>
her off before, hee had taken from her the time of repentance. Thus after he had threatned a Deluge and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto the old world, hee gaue them many yeeres to repent, before hee waſht them away with the waters of his wrath. He gaue <hi>Sodom</hi> &amp; <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> two ſinfull Cities, hee gaue them a time to repent. <hi>Niniue</hi> had a time, <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> had a time, two and fortie yeeres after the paſſion of Chriſt, the Figge Tree had a time,<note place="margin">Chryſ. ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruat.</note> the <hi>fooliſh fiue Virgins</hi> had a <hi>time</hi> when they might haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, nay, God giues a time, and lends a long ſpace vnto the moſt prophane, to make them the more inexcuſable; Curſed <hi>Cain,</hi> prophane <hi>Eſau,</hi> deſperate <hi>Iudas,</hi> they had all a time. This graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous proceeding doth the Lord ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and keepe, and will vnto the worlds end; hee giues vnto ſome of vs twenty yeeres, vnto ſome thirty, vnto ſome forty, vnto ſome fifty, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till gray-headed Age, the bloſſome of the graue,<note place="margin">Hec mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum vnde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>det aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas, Aug.</note> bids vs prepare our win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſheete. And if in all this time, which in all is but a ſpanne, a moment, a ſmall ſcantling, wee let it ſlippe vntill
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:19157:68"/>
our glaſſe bee all runne out, and the thred of our life cleane cut off; then are wee left without excuſe, and our end is damnation. The children of this world are wiſe in their generation, they take their time and opportunity. The Marchant buyeth while the Mart laſteth, the Souldier fighteth while the battell indureth: the Husband-man ſoweth while it is winter, reapeth when it is ſummer. That faithfull mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of time, heauens great Orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, obſerueth his riſing and ſetting. The Sunne, the Moone and Starres keepe their conſtant reuolution according to the will of their Maker, in the firſt Creation; <hi>The Storke, the Turtle, and the Crane know their appointed time, Ierem.</hi> 8.7. But man neglects his time, and lets it ſteale away one day after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vntill the day of grace bee cloſed vpon him. Wee are called vpon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in the dayes of our youth, before ſin is habituated, &amp; cuſtome of ſinning hath taken away the ſenſe of ſinne. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1. But men for the moſt part refuſe to repent vntill they
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:19157:69"/>
be old, and ſo by a iuſt iudgement of God, they goe downe to the <hi>graue, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their bones full of the ſinnes of their youth</hi>; for how almoſt is it poſſible that we ſhould repent truely, when wee be old? repentance is ſo hard and difficult a thing, a heauy burthen, a difficult duty; Age of it ſelfe is a burthen, a ſickneſſe, a languiſhing diſeaſe: the Sergeants and Officers of Death haue arreſted e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery limbe, &amp; haue taken vp the whole body, as an habitation of death. One crieth with the <hi>Shunamites</hi> child,<note place="margin">Non vita longa, ſed longa aegritudo.</note> Alas, my head, alas, my head, another with with <hi>Antiochus,</hi> My belly, my belly, the third with <hi>Aſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Shaking Palſie.</note> My feet, my feete: this mans limbs tremble as a reed ſhaken with the winde, another mans limbes are like the dead boughes of a dying barke,<note place="margin">Dead Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</note> one laboureth in one diſeaſe, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in another one in the chollicke, another in the ſtone; this mans eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to waxe dimme, his eares deafe, his wind-pipes euen ſtopt vp with flegme, his teeth falling out of his head, his hands poſſeſt with the palſie, his legges not able to beare vp his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, his knees ſtrike one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:19157:69"/>
his backe not able to beare the waight of a Graſhopper: and when man is brought vnto ſuch an exigent that hee cannot put off, or put on his owne clothes, how ſhall he put off ſins, and put on newneſſe of life? Surely, I ſee not how he can repent, vnleſſe hee repents that he hath liued too long, and therfore they wiſh for welcome death: when little doe they well conſider, that death is the diſſolution of a miſerable life, but a paſſage to a worſe, a gate, an entrance to hell, if they dye vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> his counſell in this caſe is very heauenly, and very worthy to be embraced.<note place="margin">Lib. de V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitat. poen. agend.</note> 
               <hi>Age poenitentiam dum ſanus es, ſi ſic agis, dico tibi quod ſecurus es, quia poenitentiam egiſti eo tempore quo peccare potuiſti: ſi vis agere poeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, quando iam peccare non potes, pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata te dimiſerunt, non tu illa:</hi> Repent while thou art in good health, if thou doſt ſo, I tell thee, thou art ſafe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tedſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou couldſt haue ſinned; if thou doſt repent, when by reaſon of the weakeneſſe of thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, thou art not able to performe the workes of darkneſſe, ſinne hath left
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:19157:70"/>
to ſaue mee.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>Repent therefore, that thy ſinnes may bee done away, when the time of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of God.</hi> and that with all ſpeede. <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> bad <hi>Moſes</hi> pray for him to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: but doe thou repent to day, thou knoweſt not whether thou ſhalt liue vntil to morrow, thy life is but a flower flouriſhing to day, fading to morrow, but a bubble ſoone blowne vp, ſoone blowne out: thou maiſt dine in all thy royalty with <hi>Balthaſar,</hi> carouſe in gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den bowles, yet ere thy dinner be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſuch is the vncertainty of our flee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting life, thy ſoule may bee diuorced from thy body, and thy body fit for no company, but the wormes. It is not to morrow that God requireth, but to day: To day if you wil heare my voice, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.15. Remember that there will be a day, when there will be iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t without mercy, when, if thou neglectſt this day of ſaluation, this acceptable ſeaſon, thou ſhalt bee caſt to Hell, and there ſhalt lye in miſery, howling, and crying out, O miſerable wretch that I am, what did I meane, that I did not confeſſe my ſins, repent and turne
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:19157:70"/>
to God, when I was vpon earth? now I ſee others partakers of heauenly ioyes, and I thruſt out and caſt into theſe miſerable torments; where thou ſhalt bee inforced to ſay, O how iuſt are Gods iudgements! I was ſpoken vnto, but I would not heare: I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed out of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and intreated by the Miniſters of Chriſt to repent; but I ſtopped mine eares againſt their admonitions. How doe I iuſtly feele that, which nothing could make me feare? Let vs not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neglect this opportunity, this ſpace which is our life time, &amp; a time which God in mercy hath allotted vnto vs to repent in: after this time repentance will neuer be preached any more, nor ſinnes pardoned.<note place="margin">Nazian.</note> 
               <hi>Hic namque peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum remiſſio, vbi peccatorum commiſſio, hic nobis prompt a medela eſt, post autem clauſa eſt omnis medicinae falutis,</hi> For ſinnes are remitted here, where as they were committed. Heere onely haue wee the <hi>Balme</hi> of <hi>Gilead</hi> to cure the wounds of a ſinfull ſoule, but hereafter all medicines of ſaluation ſhall bee lockt from vs, and we from them. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:19157:71"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Baſil.</note> 
               <hi>Baſil</hi>: This preſent time in which wee liue, is the time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and remiſſion of ſinnes. <hi>Fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra ſibi homo poſt hoc corpus promittit, quod in hoc corpore comparare neglexit, Auguſtine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> And therefore in vaine doth man promiſe vnto himſelfe, that after this life, which he doth neglect to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this life. This is our day, the next is the Lords day, wherein he wil come to iudge euery man according to his wayes; as the Tree groweth, ſo it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and as it falleth, ſo it lyeth; as men liue, ſo they die, and as they die, ſo they come to Iudgement. In what ſinnes ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer wee dye vnrepented of, in the ſame ſhall wee bee iudged and condemned. Let vs learne therefore, in our growth to grow the right way, let vs looke toward Ieruſalem, growe toward heauen, that is, let vs liue wel, that wee may dye well: ſo that at the worlds generall Iudgement, at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the iuſt, wee may <hi>meet our Sauiour in the ayre, and be euer with him,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come, Lord Ieſus, come quickely.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19157:73"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19157:73"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19157:74"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19157:74"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19157:75"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19157:75"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19157:76"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19157:76"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19157:77"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19157:77"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19157:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19157:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19157:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19157:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19157:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19157:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19157:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19157:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19157:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:19157:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:19157:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:19157:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:19157:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:19157:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19157:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19157:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:19157:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:19157:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:19157:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:19157:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:19157:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:19157:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
